<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://jburz2001.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://jburz2001.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-11-20T19:37:19+00:00</updated><id>https://jburz2001.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Justin Burzachiello&apos;s personal website. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">X–Ray Computed Tomography (IN PROGRESS)</title><link href="https://jburz2001.github.io/blog/2025/x-ray-computed-tomography/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="X–Ray Computed Tomography (IN PROGRESS)"/><published>2025-11-15T14:14:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-11-15T14:14:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jburz2001.github.io/blog/2025/x-ray-computed-tomography</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jburz2001.github.io/blog/2025/x-ray-computed-tomography/"><![CDATA[<p>Source of thumbnail image: https://yxlon.comet.tech/en/technologies/industrial-ct.</p> <h1 id="introduction">Introduction</h1> <p>3D imaging is a powerful experimental tool with many modalities, including magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), and X–ray computed tomography (CT), and more. Each of these has pros and cons; for instance, MRI scanners do not leverage ionizing radiation to form images but the devices themselves require expensive and increasingly scarce cryogenic liquids to cool the superconducting magnet inside of the scanner.</p> <p>X–ray CT was first developed in the early 1970s, with the invention credited to Sir Godfrey Hounsfield and Dr. Allan Cormack, who were awarded the Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine in 1979 for their contributions. While the first CT scanners were designed for medical imaging, over the decades, advancements in CT technology in resolution, speed, and accessibility have expanded its applications beyond medicine into fields such as manufacturing, archaeology, and botany. I refer to the use of CT in non–medical applications as “industrial CT.” Note that I refer to X–ray CT when I say CT but that CT can be performed with visible light, neutrons, and more.</p> <p>This blog post details the principles of X–ray computed tomography (CT) that I learned as a CT systems engineer intern at VJ Technologies, an engineering firm that focuses on X–ray–based non–destructive testing for industrial and scientific applications.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-4 col-md-4 mt-3 mt-md-0 text-center"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/ct_tutorial/first_radiograph-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/ct_tutorial/first_radiograph-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/ct_tutorial/first_radiograph-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/ct_tutorial/first_radiograph.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1 d-block mx-auto" width="100%" height="auto" title="First radiograph" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> The first X--ray radiograph that was imaged by Wilhelm Conrad Roentgen in 1895. Source: https://www.atlasobscura.com/articles/roentgen-xrays-discovery-radiographs. </div> <h1 id="ct-scanning">CT Scanning</h1> <p>CT scans are reconstructed from 2D X–ray images called radiographs taken at various angles. The following section describes the exact process taken to do this, including the required relative motion of the object being scanned and the X–ray source/detector, radiography, and filtered back projection.</p> <h2 id="looking-at-an-object-from-different-angles">Looking at an Object From Different Angles</h2> <p>A CT scan works by revolving an X–ray source and detector around an object while capturing X–ray radiographs at each angle. Equivalently, the X–ray source and detector can be fixed in place while the object being scanned is rotated. In medical CT, it is advantageous to keep the patient fixed in place while the X–ray source and detector revolve around them, but you might find it funny to imagine the opposite case with you being slowly rotated at the doctor’s office. The CT scanners I used for industrial CT fixed the X–ray source and detector while rotating the object being scanned. This is often the most economical and maintainable option since the mechanical structure only needs to hold the source and detector in place.</p> <p>To understand how this works intuitively, imagine you wanted to inspect the 3D structure of a chair. To do so, you would walk around it and perceive 2D images of it which you use in your brain to reconstruct an image of its 3D structure. You could also sit still while a friend rotates the chair in front of you. You likely understand that you don’t need to look at the chair from 1000 different angles to picture its 3D structure in your mind’s eye—3 angles might suffice! This alludes to an active field of research in applied mathematics called compressive sensing which, in the context of CT, involves reconstructing 3D images from a very small number of 2D images. Similarly, in deep learning–based computer vision, there exist so–called neural radiance fields (NeRFs) that use deep learning to represent a 3D scene from a small set of 2D images.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/ct_tutorial/industrial_ct-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/ct_tutorial/industrial_ct-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/ct_tutorial/industrial_ct-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/ct_tutorial/industrial_ct.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Industrial CT" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/ct_tutorial/medical_ct-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/ct_tutorial/medical_ct-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/ct_tutorial/medical_ct-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/ct_tutorial/medical_ct.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Medical CT" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Industrial CT (left) vs medical CT (right). Source: https://www.matsusada.com/column/ct-tech1.html. </div> <h2 id="radiography">Radiography</h2> <p>At each angle of the rotation/revolution, a radiograph is taken. This is a 2D grayscale image that quantifies how much of the X–ray radiation penetrated the object. Areas of lower density in the field of view will exhibit higher intensity in the radiograph since more photons of X–ray radiation will pass through that section and enter the active area of the detector, which is basically its “retina.” Conversely, regions of high density will attenuate the incident X–ray photons to a greater extent than lower-density regions, yielding relatively low intensity exiting X–ray radiation and thus relatively–low intensity values in the corresponding area of the radiograph. High-density regions can completely block X–rays, similar to how a concrete wall is opaque to visible light. However, objects are more transparent to higher–energy X–rays and, importantly, different substances exhibit different X–ray opacities. One of the jobs of a CT scanner operator is to master this interplay of X–ray energy and X–ray opacity: using X–rays with energy that are too low will render the object being scanned opaque to them, and radiographs will not be able to see inside of the object; using X–rays with energy that are too high will render the object being scanned transparent to them, and radiographs will not even see the object being scanned; using X–rays with just the right energy will render the object being scanned partially transparent so that there is contrast between different substances in the radiograph.</p> <p>Notably, substances with higher densities will be more opaque to X–ray radiation. This is why lead—a very dense substance—is used to create shielding for X–ray vaults and personal protective equipment. However, interestingly enough, lead is too dense for its own good when it comes to structural integrity, as it becomes brittle under its own weight. Thus, structures are built with a layer of lead but mainly with some other material for structural integrity, like concrete.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/ct_tutorial/PCB-CT-Scan-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/ct_tutorial/PCB-CT-Scan-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/ct_tutorial/PCB-CT-Scan-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/ct_tutorial/PCB-CT-Scan.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="CT scan of hard drive" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/ct_tutorial/Hard-Drive-CT-Scan-Electronics-Auto-Space-Exp-Defense-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/ct_tutorial/Hard-Drive-CT-Scan-Electronics-Auto-Space-Exp-Defense-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/ct_tutorial/Hard-Drive-CT-Scan-Electronics-Auto-Space-Exp-Defense-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/ct_tutorial/Hard-Drive-CT-Scan-Electronics-Auto-Space-Exp-Defense.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="CT scan of PCB" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> CT scans obtained from radiographs. Printed circuit board (left) and hard drive (right). Source: https://vjt.com/industries/electronics/. </div> <h2 id="radiographs-as-projections">Radiographs as Projections</h2> <p>In the context of CT, these aforementioned radiographs are often called “projections” because the intensity value registered by a detector element (dexel) is the initial intensity of the X–ray beam with exponential decay through each material it travels through without information about where such decay occurred. For a single substance of length $x$, the formula for the intensity is $I = I_0 e^{-\mu x}$, where $\mu$ is a function of density for that substance called the linear attenuation coefficient. For a discretized 1-dimensional path with a finite number of substances, this formula becomes $I = I_0 e^{-(\mu_1 x_1 + \mu_2 x_2 + \ldots + \mu_N x_N)}$. For a continuum domain with an infinite number of infinitesimally small substances, this formula becomes $I = I_0 e^{-\int \mu(x)\,dx}$. Notably, the evaluation of these formulas summates/integrates out the information about space. Thus, the intensity values registered on a radiograph contain no information about where in an X–ray beam’s trajectory the X–ray encountered a region of particular density—it only knows the result of the entire path! Information about attenuation is thus “projected” along the direction of X–ray propagation onto the dexel.</p> <h2 id="back-projection">Back Projection</h2> <p>Importantly, if one obtains many projections at different angles, such as 1200 projection images, each equidistantly spaced at an angle between 0 and 180 degrees, then spatial information about the density of the object can be recovered. As alluded to earlier, this general process of converting 2D radiographs/projections into a 3D scan is called “reconstruction.”</p> <p>A significant step in the reconstruction process is “back projection,” which involves taking the value registered at a dexel and populating all locations along the path in the direction that the X–ray was measured (i.e., co–linear with the ray path). This effectively un–projects the X–ray intensity by assigning all locations that would have contributed to its value with the resulting value. However, this makes no distinction between different locations along the path. Therefore, if an X–ray passed through both air and wood, both the air and wood would be assigned the same value registered by the dexel, even though the wood exhibits a greater density and thus a higher linear attenuation coefficient and greater degree of X–ray opacity/attenuation. To overcome this and obtain information about density in the object space, back projection must be performed on each of the projections obtained during the CT scan. The result will be a 3D image called a “reconstruction” with values proportional to the densities of the substances at different locations in the space. However, if one performs this reconstruction by only naively following these previous steps, then the result will be very blurry and unacceptable for analysis. Thus, an additional step involving filtering the projections is necessary.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/ct_tutorial/back_projection-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/ct_tutorial/back_projection-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/ct_tutorial/back_projection-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/ct_tutorial/back_projection.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Back projection" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Un--filtered back projection. Subfigure (a) shows the ideal result; subfigures (b--f) show results of un--filtered back projection with increasing numbers of projections used for reconstruction. Source: https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1934592519300607. </div> <h2 id="filtered-back-projection">Filtered Back Projection</h2> <p>Filtered back projection (FBP) is the process of filtering projection data to back–project it to an accurate reconstruction. The filter in question is a 1–dimensional digital signal sharpening filter (e.g., Ram–Lak ramp filter, Shepp–Logan windowed filter). To perform FBP, it is helpful to store all the projection data in a single data structure called a sinogram. In a sinogram, the abscissa (x-axis) designates the dexel, while the ordinate (y-axis) denotes the rotation angle. A sinogram is constructed row-by-row, where each collection of intensity values registered on all the dexels at some angle is formed into a row and stacked on top of one another as the angle iterates from 0 to 180 degrees. For FBP, the blur present in the original back projection can be massively reduced by sharpening the sinogram row-wise with a 1D digital sharpening filter. Applying the previously described back projection process with data from this filtered sinogram will yield a 3D reconstruction image that is far less blurry. The overall FBP process is a large reason for the word “computed” in computed tomography.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/ct_tutorial/filtered_back_projection-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/ct_tutorial/filtered_back_projection-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/ct_tutorial/filtered_back_projection-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/ct_tutorial/filtered_back_projection.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Filtered back projection" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Filtered back projection. Subfigure (a) shows the ideal result; subfigures (b--f) show results of filtered back projection with increasing numbers of projections used for reconstruction. Source: https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1934592519300607. </div> <h1 id="ct-artifacts">CT Artifacts</h1> <p>In the ideal world, CT reconstructions would be unaffected by motion, CT scanner limitations, or material properties of the substances being scanned. Unfortunately, these factors can cause distortions or inaccuracies that appear in the reconstructions, yet do not exist physically, called artifacts. They are sort of like hallucinations of the CT scanner. These artifacts compromise the quality and reliability of reconstruction results and are thus important to understand, circumvent, and mitigate. There are many types of CT artifacts and each stems from a different source yet multiple artifacts can be present simultaneously. Here I describe the following artifacts: motion, ring, streak, and beam hardening. Understanding these artifacts is crucial for those interpreting CT results since one must differentiate between artifacts and their lack thereof to ensure accurate analysis.</p> <h2 id="motion-artifacts">Motion Artifacts</h2> <p>Motion artifacts are exhibitions of blurring due to movement of the object being scanned or the scanner itself during the imaging process. This can result in blurred or distorted images because the structures being scanned do not appear in the same position across the projections. Intuitively, if there is motion during the acquisition of projections, the FBP back–projects information about a single location in the object’s physical space to multiple locations in the reconstruction, yielding a blurred effect. Sources of motion are less common in industrial CT compared with medical CT (since medical CT scans involve scanning living beings) but can still occur. For instance, an inanimate object can wobble due to centrifugal force upon it during its rotation on a turntable during a scan, or heavy machinery can shake the X–ray detector during operation. These motion artifacts can obscure details and make it challenging—if not impossible—to accurately analyze the reconstruction.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/ct_tutorial/motion_artifact-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/ct_tutorial/motion_artifact-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/ct_tutorial/motion_artifact-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/ct_tutorial/motion_artifact.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Motion artifact" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Motion artifact. Subfigure (A) shows an ideal slice of a CT scan; subfigure (B) shows the same slice of a CT scan, but obtained under influence of motion. Source: https://www.frontiersin.org/journals/neurology/articles/10.3389/fneur.2017.00232/full. </div> <h2 id="ring-artifacts">Ring Artifacts</h2> <p>Ring artifacts are caused by the malfunction of dexels during CT operation, and they appear as concentric circles (i.e., rings) around the center of the CT reconstruction image. The circular geometry of these artifacts is due to the rotation of the scanner around the object being scanned. Basically, if one or more dexels are miscalibrated or broken, then they will register erroneous X–ray intensity values. If such a dexel registers this error at each angle of object rotation during the CT scan, then these errors will be back-projected into the CT reconstruction as a circular structure with the intensity of this erroneous reading, where the circular structure appears around the central axis of rotation. Thus, the circular geometric appearance of ring artifacts results from the combination of rotational scanning and persistent errors from malfunctioning detectors.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-4 col-md-4 mt-3 mt-md-0 text-center"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/ct_tutorial/ring_artifact-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/ct_tutorial/ring_artifact-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/ct_tutorial/ring_artifact-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/ct_tutorial/ring_artifact.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Ring artifact" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Ring artifact. Notice the ring--shaped, non--anatomical structure near the middle of this brain scan. Source: https://radiopaedia.org/cases/ring-artifact-3. </div> <h2 id="streak-artifacts">Streak Artifacts</h2> <p>Streak artifacts are bright or dark lines of intensity emanating from high-density objects within a CT scan. Unlike ring and motion artifacts, streak artifacts can be difficult to avoid. This is because streak artifacts occur due to X–ray physics of Compton scattering and/or beam hardening rather than the environmental setup of the CT scan. However, they can be mitigated with image post-processing techniques and metal artifact reduction (MAR) algorithms (even if the artifacts are not caused by metal).</p> <p>Intuitively, they occur when low–enough–energy X–rays encounter a dense–enough object, and thus scatter off of it. An example of this is when performing a CT scan on low-density plant roots where the plant was grown in soil with rocks. During the growth of the plant, the roots will latch on to small rocks in their vicinity. Even if the root is completely removed from the soil, some rocks will still remain in their grasp. During the CT scan, these rocks will be of a much higher density than the plant root. Now, while it is true that using high–energy X–rays would mitigate the streak artifacts generated by these rocks, doing so makes the plant roots transparent to the X–rays and thus unresolvable in the reconstruction used to analyze the 3D structure of the roots! Thus, the low–density of the plant root itself mandates using very low–energy X–rays to visualize them, which in turn creates streak artifacts when these low–energy X–rays encounter the rocks and Compton scatter off of them. Unfortunately, such streak artifacts can be extreme enough to make their intensity on the reconstruction indistinguishable from that of the plant roots.</p> <p>Beam hardening streak artifacts are similar to the aforementioned Compton scatter–produced streak artifacts in that they are due to X–ray energy, but these are caused by absorption instead of scattering. These artifacts occur when X–rays passing through a relatively dense substance “harden” (i.e., lower–energy photons are absorbed during transmission through the material but higher–energy photons make it through). Ideally, the X–ray energy spectrum would uniformly attenuate during transport through media; however, some energies are absorbed more than others since materials serve as a “high-pass filter” to X–rays. This results in an increased average energy of the X–rays as they exit the body, leading to inaccuracies in the reconstructed image since substances are more transparent to a higher-average energy X–ray. In circumstances with extremely dense substances, photon starvation may occur where the extremely dense substance in question nearly fully attenuates the incident X–ray beam, resulting in few, if any, photons exiting from it towards the detector, yielding dark areas in the scan that are essentially X–ray shadows.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-4 col-md-4 mt-3 mt-md-0 text-center"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/ct_tutorial/streak_artifact-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/ct_tutorial/streak_artifact-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/ct_tutorial/streak_artifact-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/ct_tutorial/streak_artifact.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Streak artifact" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Streak artifact. Notice the bright thin lines due to scatter. Source: https://radiopaedia.org/cases/gunshot-wound-to-face-old-1#image-6170651. </div> <h1 id="ct-scan-workflow">CT Scan Workflow</h1> <p>Performing a CT scan requires taking various steps to set up and perform the scan. The following section is written from the point of view of an operator of the VEDA CORE CT machine using vi5 software, both engineered by VJ Technologies. However, the steps presented are applicable to other machines. These steps include warm–up, geometry alignment, detector calibration, preheat, actuation, and scan. Once these steps have been completed, the operator can run a CT scan on the object that they wish to scan.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-4 col-md-4 mt-3 mt-md-0 text-center"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/ct_tutorial/veda_core_CT_scanner-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/ct_tutorial/veda_core_CT_scanner-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/ct_tutorial/veda_core_CT_scanner-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/ct_tutorial/veda_core_CT_scanner.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Veda Core CT scanner" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Veda Core CT scanner. Source: https://vjt.com/products/veda-core/. </div> <h2 id="warmup">Warm–up</h2> <p>The warm–up phase is the first step of using a CT machine. This step involves ramping both the filament current and tube voltage gradually, from lowest to highest, in order to ensure that the machine can achieve them without extraneous strain on the system that might damage it. To understand how it works, it helps to understand the basic physics of how the X–rays are generated. Inside of the X–ray source is a filament which boils off electrons when heated. The temperature of the filament is set by the CT operator as a current parameter of the X–ray source. This is like how running a current through a wire will warm it up–in the case of the CT filament, it warms up and boils off electrons. Importantly, these electrons are charged particles, so they can be accelerated in some direction if a voltage is applied across some region. This is like how an object with mass will roll downhill due to gravity. However, in the case of electrons, they roll up the electrostatic potential “hill” due to their negative charge, where a difference in values of this potential is called a “voltage.” Intuitively, a larger voltage corresponds to a steeper slope on the potential landscape, causing electrons to accelerate faster. The CT operator controls this voltage, and it effectively determines the energy of the X–rays generated due to stronger impacts of the electrons on a target. For generating very high–energy X–rays necessary for CT scanning incredibly dense materials, like part of the chassis of a rocket, klystrons and other devices are used to build particle accelerators.</p> <p>Often, the aforementioned accelerated electrons are directed at an angled block of tungsten. Upon near collision with the tungsten, the electrons slow down due to electrostatic repulsion, generating bremsstrahlung, also known as “braking radiation.” The bremsstrahlung is high-energy X–ray radiation generated due to the conservation of energy. The electrons have a continuous spectrum of kinetic energy due to motion, but they slow down due to electrostatic interaction with atoms in tungsten. This lost energy is thus converted into an electromagnetic form that is a convenient source of a continuous spectrum of X–rays. Characteristic X–rays are a separate source of X–ray radiation due to electrons colliding with a target, but they occur due to quantum mechanical effects rather than classical bremsstrahlung. These X–rays exhibit characteristic spikes in X–ray energy spectra with higher–energies than the bremsstrahlung.</p> <p>But why do I need to run the warm–up when starting up a CT machine? Well, if one were to suddenly make the temperature of the electron source filament very high relative to what it was, then there is a risk of it getting damaged. This is like how runners are recommended to stretch before running since they could injure muscles if they suddenly subject them to strenuous exercise without warming up.</p> <p>Importantly, the X–rays used for CT can actually damage the detector over time. Thus, during the warm–up phase when X–rays are generated without a need to use them for imaging, it is good practice to shield the detector from them. I do so with a lead brick placed in front of the detector, blocking X–ray radiation from the X–ray source. This is like how one might have a lead bib placed on them at the dentist when getting X–rays done in order to protect their vital organs, but here the lead is used to protect the detector since it doesn’t need to detect anything.</p> <h2 id="detector-calibration">Detector Calibration</h2> <p>After warming up, one needs to ensure that the X–ray detector is calibrated to the intensity of X–ray radiation from the X–ray source. Doing so helps ensure accurate readings and prevent ring artifacts. To perform detector calibration, one needs to first ensure that the detector has a clear field of view of the X–ray source by removing any obstructions between them. Next, the operator must set the X–ray source to have the values of voltage, current, and integration time that they expect to use during the scan. After that, the operator must wait until the detector has adjusted its readings to the new mean intensity registered at the detector. Afterwards, the operator should turn off the X–ray source altogether to let the detector register its X–ray readings when the source is off (basically, to compute statistics about the background noise). Finally, the CT scanner software will calibrate the dexels based on information gathered in the previous steps.</p> <h2 id="geometry-alignment">Geometry Alignment</h2> <p>After the detector calibration phase is the geometry alignment segment. This portion is necessary for obtaining accurate reconstructions, but one can obtain radiographs just fine without doing it. In order to get an accurate CT scan, it is necessary for the software doing the reconstruction to have knowledge of the geometry of the setup: the distance between the source and object, called the source-object-distance (SOD); the distance between the source and the detector, called the source-detector-distance (SDD); in addition to the misalignment of the center of the source relative to the center of the detector along the x–, y–, and z–axes. These quantities are obtained through geometry alignment. However, to actually perform geometry alignment, one must acquire a scannable object with a very precisely defined geometry which can be hardcoded into the software of the CT scanner. When I did CT, I used a so-called alignment rod filled with steel ball bearings of known radius and distance from one another. Upon scanning this rod as a “geometry alignment” scan, the software detects the ball bearings and deduces the location of the rod based on how the radius it perceives compares to the radius it knows and how the distance between the bearings it perceives compares to the distance it knows. From this information, it can deduce where the rod is and compute the geometric quantities that are necessary for CT reconstruction. Other objects can be used too.</p> <p>Now why exactly must geometry alignment be done with a particular object with geometry hard–coded into the software? Well, imagine that you want to gauge the size of a quarter by looking at it. A quarter right in front of your eye will look quite large but a quarter 10 feet away will look quite small in comparison. However, you, as a human who knows what a quarter is, understand that the quarter has a very specific size and that it will look smaller if it’s further away. Thus, you can deduce how far away it is at a given time based on how large it appears in your field of view! In a CT scanner, the hard–coded geometry is the CT scanner’s “knowledge” about the size of an object, and when it perceives it can then deduce how far it is based on how large it appears in its field of view. This enables the CT scanner to compute geometric quantities necessary for reconstruction, like the source–object–distance.</p> <p>Importantly, if a CT reconstruction is desired, then geometry alignment must be redone each time that the SOD or SDD is changed. Additionally, before actually performing geometry alignment, the operator should place the object that they would like to scan onto the turntable and adjust the location of the object so that it fits into the field of view at all angles. Only after completing this step should the geometry be aligned, since running geometry alignment effectively tells the scanner to use the current SOD, SDD, and misalignment values.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/ct_tutorial/geometry_alignment-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/ct_tutorial/geometry_alignment-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/ct_tutorial/geometry_alignment-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/ct_tutorial/geometry_alignment.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Geometry alignment" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Identifying new and better objects for geometry alignment is an active area of research. Subfigure (a) shows a particular type of geometry alignment object; subfigure (b) shows a more--novel type of geometry alignment object, along with what the overall structure looks like. Each object has well--defined, unambiguous geometry to enable geometry calibration for reconstruction. Source: https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1088/1361-6501/ac38ef. </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="numerical-methods"/><category term="imaging"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[TODO figures, proofreading]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Latent Manifolds From the Taylor Series Expansion (IN PROGRESS)</title><link href="https://jburz2001.github.io/blog/2025/latent-manifolds-from-the-taylor-series-expansion/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Latent Manifolds From the Taylor Series Expansion (IN PROGRESS)"/><published>2025-11-14T14:14:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-11-14T14:14:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jburz2001.github.io/blog/2025/latent-manifolds-from-the-taylor-series-expansion</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jburz2001.github.io/blog/2025/latent-manifolds-from-the-taylor-series-expansion/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="latent-variables-of-a-dynamical-system">Latent Variables of a Dynamical System</h2> <p>Computational physics simulations often solve large systems of coupled ordinary differential equations (ODEs). Such systems may naturally model the physics (e.g., molecular dynamics); othertimes, they may result from a method of lines discretization of an unsteady state partial differential equation (PDE)—discretion in space but not in time. Regardless of their origin, these systems abound and can be modeled as a deceptively simple equation:</p> \[\begin{equation} \frac{d\mathbf{y}}{dt} = \mathbf{f}(x, t), \end{equation}\] <p>where $\mathbf{y}$ is the state of the dynamical system, $t$ is time, and $f$ is the so–called vector field of the dynamical system that models how the state evolves over time.</p> <p>In this dynamical system, $\mathbf{y} = \mathbf{y}(t)\in\mathbb{R}^{N}$ since the state has $N$ degrees of freedom. As an example, let’s say an engineer wants to model the diffusion of temperature through a 12–inch metal rod after a candle is placed near it at the left. In real–life there are an uncountably infinite number of positions along the rod: $1.1$in from the left, $1.11$in from the left, $1.111$in from the left, and so on ad infinitum. This means that one can analytically model the system’s temperature as a function—an infinite dimensional vector—of space and time, yielding the following PDE:</p> \[\begin{equation} \frac{\partial T}{\partial t} = \nu \frac{\partial^2}{\partial x^2} T, \end{equation}\] <p>where $\nu$ is a diffusion constant quantifying the thermal conductivity of the rod, $\frac{\partial^2}{\partial x^2}$ is a 2nd–order partial differential operator in space, and $T\in\mathbb{R}^{\infty}$ is temperature modeled as a function of location $x$ and time $t$. The algebraic structure of this equation and the spectral properties of the differential operators encode the physics.</p> <p>Computers, however, have limited memory, so the aforementioned infinite continuum of positions along the 1D rod must be discretized into a finite collection of cells spanning the 12–inches of space. The number of discretization cells is effectively the spatial resolution of the computational physics model. Using the method of lines to semi–discretize the 1D linear heat equation yields the following system of ODEs:</p> \[\begin{equation} \frac{d\mathbf{y}}{dt} = \nu \mathbf{A} \mathbf{y}, \end{equation}\] <p>where $\mathbf{y}\in\mathbb{R}^N$ with $N$ being the number of discretization cells.</p> <p>The integer, $N$, is arbitrary, but larger values correspond to higher spatial resolution, which may be necessary for resolving details. Unfortunately, increasing $N$ increases computational costs in both memory and time since more data must be stored and processed. This is just like how having a 4K resolution image of me is great since you have $N = 3840 \times 2160 = 8,294,400$ pixels to resolve fine details with but such a 4K image requires much more storage than a Full HD image with $N = 1920 \times 1080 = 2,073,600$ pixels.</p> <p>The number $N$ is arbitrary—you can still simulate diffusion with $N=10$, $N=100$, or $N=1,000,000$! Importantly though, the actual physics are aptly modeled with a small number of latent variables that we don’t directly observe. In other words, even though we have $n$ physical observables (i.e., the temperature readings at each of our $n$ cells), there are actually be $n\ll N$ latent variables that evolve over time! This is best understood geometrically: the state of a dynamical system can be envisioned as a point in $\mathbb{R}^N$ that flies around over time; in physics, the path traced out happens to be some curve in low–dimensional surface. To better imagine this concept, put your index finger on your nose then move your finger back and forth as if you were tracing out Pinoccio’s nose. This curve you traced out with your finger is a 1–dimensional curve embedded in a 3–dimensional space, so positions along the curve can aptly be described with a single latent variable, that being the “distance from nose” instead of 3 different physical observables $x$, $y$, and $z$! In physics, the same logic applies, but we can take computer simulations with hundreds of millions of physical observables but simulate them in the latent manifolds rather than in the high–dimensional physical observable space, yielding astronomial speedups. As an example, researchers have taken a soft robot with $N\approx 800,000$ degrees of freedom but controlled it by actuating $n=2$ latent variables.</p> <p>The identification and use of latent manifolds from data is a field of machine learning called dimensionality reduction; it is paramount to model order reduction in computational physics, principal component analysis in statistics, and autoencoder architectures in deep learning–based artificial intelligence. This post discusses how to infer latent manifolds from snapshots of the state of a physical system under the assumption that the manifold is well–modeled by a Taylor series expansion. In doing so, we will derive the data–driven optimization problem used to infer what some researchers in model order reduction call a polynomial manifold but others call a spectral submanifold.</p> <h2 id="the-taylor-series-expansion">The Taylor Series Expansion</h2> <p>Recall that our goal is to sample the state of a dynamical system’s physical observables over time and use these data to parameterize a “surface” upon which our data live. The word surface is used loosely here since it can be 1–dimensional (a curve), 2–dimensional (a fabric), or of any higher dimension. These surfaces are called manifolds and possess important mathematical structure that is the subject of immense study in mathematics through differential geometry, topology, and more. Regardless, it helps to make assumptions on our inferred parameterization of a latent manifold, such as its dimensionality and nonlinearity. Assuming that our latent manifold is a function of the corresponding system’s latent variables, we can impose different functions as structures to represent it. In this post we’ll assume the parameterization as a power series function of latent variables; more specifically, as a Taylor series function of latent variables.</p> <p>Taylor’s Theorem states that an $m$ times continuously differentiable function can be approximated by its $n$th degree Taylor polynomial plus a remainder. This post assumes (for simplicity) that the latent manifold under study is an analytic function such that it is infinitely differentiable and possesses a convergent Taylor series expansion about every point, but this is not true for all dynamical systems since not all vector fields are analytic. Researchers in the spectral submanifold community strongly emphasize the importance of the continuous differentiability of the Taylor series latent manifold but others those who call these latent manifolds polynomial manifolds tend to not do so.</p> <p>Let’s first define the Taylor series expansion of a multivariate, vector–valued function, $\mathbf{y}:\mathbb{R}^{n}\rightarrow\mathbb{R}^N$, where $(\cdot)^{\otimes p}:\mathbb{R}^N\rightarrow\mathbb{R}^{n^p}$ denotes the $p$th Kronecker power and $[\mathrm{D}^p\mathbf{y}]_{\mathbf{x}_0}$ denotes the tensor of all $p$th–order partial derivatives of elements of $\mathbf{y}$ with respect to elements of $\mathbf{x}$—each evaluated at $\mathbf{x}_0$ after derivative computation:</p> \[\begin{equation} \mathbf y(\mathbf x) = \mathbf y(\mathbf x_0) + \left[\mathrm{D}\mathbf y\right]_{\mathbf x_0}(\mathbf x - \mathbf x_0) + \frac{1}{2}\left[\mathrm{D}^2\mathbf y\right]_{\mathbf x_0}(\mathbf x - \mathbf x_0)^{\otimes2} + \cdots. \end{equation}\] <p>The rest of this post will consider the Maclaurin expansion (i.e., $\mathbf{x}_0\equiv\mathbf{0}$):</p> \[\begin{equation}\label{eqn:maclaurin_series} \mathbf y(\mathbf x) = \mathbf f(0) + \left[\mathrm{D}\mathbf y\right]_{0}\,\mathbf x + \frac{1}{2}\left[\mathrm{D}^2\mathbf y\right]_{0}\,\mathbf x^{\otimes2} + \cdots. \end{equation}\] <p>Expanding our Taylor series about the origin ensures that we can construct a non–affine subspace to serve as the abscissae of our inferred latent manifold. In particular, we will build the latent manifold as a graph over this subspace spanned by the latent variables. As we will later show, the range of the linear decoder, $\mathbf{V}_1$, can well–approximate the latent manifold’s tangent space about the origin since it is inferred from data as the aforementioned Taylor expansion’s Jacobian.</p> <p>Leveraging a Maclaurin expansion does not, however, mean that the physical observables, $\mathbf{y}_i\in\mathbb{R}^N$ naturally exist about the origin. In practice, these snapshots of the dynamical system’s state are shifted about the origin, but various methods exist to do so. In polynomial manifold literature, the mean snapshot is typically chosen as the anchor of the abscissa but the initial snapshot has also been used. However, in spectral submanifold literature, a hyperbolic fixed point of the dynamical system is shifted to the origin to anchorthe abscissa. Those familiar with linear principal component analysis (PCA) / proper orthogonal decomposition (POD) likely recognize this step of shifting data about the origin (usually using the mean datum as the origin). This is because, as we’ll see, linear PCA/POD methods construct latent manifolds as linear manifolds (i.e., subspaces) by truncating the multivariate, vector–valued Maclaurin series expansion to neglect quadratic and higher–order nonlinear structures in their data.</p> <p>The following subsections derive Taylor expansions for the different valuse of $n$ and $N$. Pardon me for using both “Taylor expansion” and “Maclaurin expansion” terminology in this post. Both terminologies are correct anyways since a Maclaurin expansion is a special case of the Taylor expansion and we will assume that our latent manifolds are constructed about the origin.</p> <h3 id="one-input-one-output-n1n1">One Input, One Output $(n=1,N=1)$</h3> <p>In this subsection we consider the Taylor expansion of a univariate, scalar–valued function, where $\mathbf{y}\equiv y$, $\mathbf{x}\equiv x$, and $\mathbf{0}\equiv 0$:</p> \[\begin{equation} \begin{aligned} \underbrace{ y(x) }_{1\times 1} &amp;= \underbrace{ y(0) }_{1\times 1} + \underbrace{ [\mathrm{D}y]_{0} }_{1\times 1}\, \underbrace{ x }_{1\times 1} + \frac{1}{2} \underbrace{ [\mathrm{D}^2y]_{0} }_{1\times 1}\, \underbrace{ x^{\otimes 2} }_{1\times 1} + \cdots\\ &amp;= f(0) + \frac{1}{2}\left[ \frac{\partial y}{\partial x}(0) \right]x + \frac{1}{2}\left[\frac{\partial^{2}y}{\partial x^{2}}(0)\right]x^{2} + \dots~,\notag \end{aligned} \end{equation}\] <p>where text below the underbraces denotes the size of the corresponding tensor.</p> <p>We can write out this result with the help of a Taylor expansion operator, $\mathcal{T}$, which represents its argument as a Maclaurin series:</p> \[\begin{equation} \begin{aligned} \mathcal{T}[\mathbf{y}] = (\mathcal{T}[y_{1}]) = \left( y_{1}(0) + \frac{\partial y_{1}}{\partial x_{1}}(0) x_{1} + \frac{1}{2}\frac{\partial^{2}y_{1}}{\partial x_{1}^{2}}(0)x_{1}^{2} + \dots \right). \end{aligned} \end{equation}\] <p>This corresponds to a dynamical system with one physical observable described by one latent variable. Dimensionality reduction would not be applied here since we are already measuing a single quantity, the minimal we could track.</p> <h3 id="one-input-multiple-outputs-n1-nneq1">One Input, Multiple Outputs $(n=1, N\neq1)$</h3> <p>Now we consider the Taylor expansion of a univariate, vector–valued function, where $\mathbf{x}\equiv x$ and $\mathbf{0}\equiv 0$:</p> \[\begin{equation} \begin{aligned} \underbrace{ \mathbf{y}(x) }_{ N\times 1 } &amp;= \underbrace{ \mathbf{y}(0) }_{ N\times 1 } + \underbrace{ [\mathrm{D}\mathbf{y}]_{0} }_{ N\times1 }\underbrace{ x }_{ 1\times 1 } + \frac{1}{2}\underbrace{ [\mathrm{D}^2\mathbf{y}]_{0} }_{ N\times1 }\underbrace{ x^{\otimes 2} }_{ 1\times 1 } + \ldots\\ &amp;= \begin{pmatrix} y_1(0)\\ y_2(0)\\ \vdots\\ y_N(0) \end{pmatrix} + \begin{pmatrix} \frac{\partial y_1}{\partial x}(0) \\ \frac{\partial y_2}{\partial x}(0)\\ \vdots \\ \frac{\partial y_N}{\partial x}(0) \end{pmatrix} x + \frac{1}{2} \begin{pmatrix} \frac{\partial^{2} y_1}{\partial x^{2}}(0) \\ \frac{\partial^{2} y_2}{\partial x^{2}}(0)\\ \vdots \\ \frac{\partial^{2} y_N}{\partial x^{2}}(0) \end{pmatrix} x^{2} + \dots~.\notag \end{aligned} \end{equation}\] <p>This shows that the Taylor expansion of a univariate, vector–valued function is a vector of Taylor expansions. We now write out the Taylor expansion of this $\mathbf{y}$ with $\mathcal{T}$:</p> \[\begin{equation} \begin{aligned}\label{eqn:taylor_vectorValuedUnivariate} \mathcal{T}[\mathbf{y}] = \begin{pmatrix} \mathcal{T}[y_{1}] \\ \mathcal{T}[y_{2}] \\ \vdots \\ \mathcal{T}[y_{N}] \end{pmatrix} = \begin{pmatrix} y_{1}(0) + \frac{\partial y_{1}}{\partial x_{1}}(0)x_{1} + \frac{1}{2}\frac{\partial^{2}y_{1}}{\partial x_{1}^{2}}(0)x_{1}^{2}+\dots \\ y_{2}(0) + \frac{\partial y_{2}}{\partial x_{1}}(0)x_{1} + \frac{1}{2}\frac{\partial^{2}y_{2}}{\partial x_{1}^{2}}(0)x_{1}^{2}+\dots \\ \vdots \\ y_{N}(0) + \frac{\partial y_{N}}{\partial x_{1}}(0)x_{1} + \frac{1}{2}\frac{\partial^{2}y_{N}}{\partial x_{1}^{2}}(0)x_{1}^{2}+\dots \end{pmatrix}. \end{aligned} \end{equation}\] <p>Here, one could envision a dynamical system with $N$ physical observables but a singular latent variable “pulling the strings” behind the scenes. Systems well–described by a singular latent variable are rather rare but it turns out that systems described by two form an important class of dynamical systems, motivating the case of $(n\neq1,\,N\neq1)$ case we are building up to. Take note that I said referred to systems “well–described” by a singular latent variable and not systems “fully–described” by a singular latent variable. This is because a single latent variable might describe most of the dynamics—perhaps even the dynamics we actually care about—but not all of the observed data.</p> <h3 id="multiple-inputs-one-output-nneq1-n1">Multiple Inputs, One Output $(n\neq1, N=1)$</h3> <p>Here we consider the Taylor expansion of a multivariate, scalar–valued function, where $\mathbf{y}\equiv y$:</p> \[\begin{equation} \begin{aligned}\label{eqn:scalar-valued,multivariate_derivation} \underbrace{ y(\mathbf{x}) }_{1\times 1} &amp;= \underbrace{ y(\mathbf{0}) }_{1\times 1} + \underbrace{ [\mathrm{D}y]_{\mathbf{0}} }_{1\times n}\,\underbrace{ \mathbf{x} }_{n\times 1} + \frac{1}{2}\underbrace{ [\mathrm{D}^2y]_{\mathbf{0}} }_{1\times n^{2}}\,\underbrace{ x^{\otimes 2} }_{n^{2}\times 1} + \ldots\\ &amp;= \underbrace{ y(\mathbf{0}) }_{1\times 1} + \underbrace{ [\mathrm{D}y]_{\mathbf{0}} }_{1\times n}\,\underbrace{ \mathbf{x} }_{n\times 1} + \frac{1}{2}\underbrace{ \mathbf{x}^{\top} }_{1\times n}\,\underbrace{ \left[ \mathrm{D}^{2}y \right]_{\mathbf{0}} }_{n\times n}\,\underbrace{ \mathbf{x} }_{n\times 1} + \ldots\notag\\ &amp;= y(\mathbf{0}) + \begin{pmatrix} \frac{\partial y}{\partial x_{1}}(\mathbf{0}) &amp;\dots &amp; \frac{\partial y}{\partial x_{n}}(\mathbf{0}) \end{pmatrix} \begin{pmatrix} x_{1} \\ \vdots \\ x_{n} \end{pmatrix} \\ &amp;\quad + \frac{1}{2} \begin{pmatrix} x_{1} &amp; \cdots &amp; x_{n} \end{pmatrix} \begin{pmatrix} \frac{\partial^{2} y}{\partial x_{1}^{2}}(\mathbf{0}) &amp; \cdots &amp; \frac{\partial^{2} y}{\partial x_{1}\partial x_{n}}(\mathbf{0}) \\ \vdots &amp; \ddots &amp; \vdots \\ \frac{\partial^{2} y}{\partial x_{n}\partial x_{1}}(\mathbf{0}) &amp; \cdots &amp; \frac{\partial^{2} y}{\partial x_{n}^{2}}(\mathbf{0}) \end{pmatrix} \begin{pmatrix} x_{1} \\ \vdots \\ x_{n} \end{pmatrix} + \cdots\notag\\ &amp;= y(\mathbf{0}) + \begin{bmatrix} \frac{\partial y}{\partial x_{1}}(\mathbf{0})x_{1} +\dots+ \frac{\partial y}{\partial x_{n}}(\mathbf{0})x_{n} \end{bmatrix} \\ &amp;\quad + \frac{1}{2}\left[ \frac{\partial^{2}y}{\partial x_{1}^{2}}(\mathbf{0})x_{1}^{2} +\dots +\frac{\partial^{2}y}{\partial x_{1}\partial x_{n}}(\mathbf{0})x_{1}x_{n} + \frac{\partial^{2}y}{\partial x_{2}\partial x_{1}}(\mathbf{0})x_{2}x_{1} + \dots \right]+\dots\notag\\ &amp;= y(\mathbf{0}) + \sum_{j=1}^{m}\left[ \frac{\partial y}{\partial x_{j}}(\mathbf{0})x_{j} \right] + \frac{1}{2} \sum_{j=1}^{m}\sum_{k=1}^{m} \left[ \frac{\partial^{2}y}{\partial x_{j}\partial x_{k}}(\mathbf{0})x_{j}x_{k} \right] + \dots\notag\\ &amp;= y(\mathbf{0})+[\mathrm{D}y]_{\mathbf{0}}[\mathbf{x}] + \frac{1}{2}[\mathrm{D}^{2}y]_{\mathbf{0}}[\mathbf{x},\mathbf{x}]+\dots\notag, \end{aligned} \end{equation}\] <p>where the last line leverages the notation of multilinear forms as functions of $\mathbf{x}$.</p> <p>We now write out the Taylor expansion of this $\mathbf{y}$ via the Taylor expansion operator $\mathcal{T}$. Notably, we take advantage of Einstein summation notation to convey the summations involved in computing this Taylor expansion:</p> \[\begin{equation} \begin{aligned}\label{eqn:taylor_scalarValuedMultivar} \mathcal{T}[y]=(\mathcal{T}[y_{1}]) = \left( y_{1}(\mathbf{0}) + J_{1j}(\mathbf{0})[x_{j}] + \frac{1}{2}H_{1jk}(\mathbf{0})[x_{j},x_{k}]+\dots \right), \end{aligned} \end{equation}\] <p>where letters $J$ and $H$ are used due to their associations with the Jacobian and Hessian, respectively.</p> <p>This case is the “anti–dimensionality reduction” case, since we have multiple latent variables describing a single physical observable, so it doesn’t make much sense to study in and of itself for dimensionality reduction. However, as we’ll soon see, this case of $(n=1, N\neq1)$ is important for deriving the Taylor expansion of a function where $(n\neq1, N\neq1)$.</p> <h3 id="multiple-inputs-multiple-ouputs-nneq1-nneq1">Multiple Inputs, Multiple Ouputs $(n\neq1, N\neq1)$</h3> <p>Finally, let’s consider the Taylor expansion of a multivariate, vector–valued function. Recall that the Taylor expansion of a vector–valued function is a vector of Taylor expansions of each element and that the Taylor expansion of a multivariate, scalar–valued function can be written concisely with Einstein summation notation. Using these principles, we arrive at the following equation for the Taylor expansion of a multivariate, vector–valued function:</p> \[\begin{equation} \begin{aligned}\label{eqn:taylor_vectorValuedMultivariate} \mathcal{T}[\mathbf{y}] = \begin{pmatrix} \mathcal{T}[y_{1}] \\ \mathcal{T}[y_{2}] \\ \dots \\ \mathcal{T}[y_{N}] \end{pmatrix} = \begin{pmatrix} y_{1}(\mathbf{0}) + G_{1j}(\mathbf{0})[x_{j}] + \frac{1}{2}H_{1jk}(\mathbf{0})[x_{j},x_{k}] + \dots \\ y_{2}(\mathbf{0}) + G_{2j}(\mathbf{0})[x_{j}] + \frac{1}{2}H_{2jk}(\mathbf{0})[x_{j},x_{k}] + \dots \\ \dots \\ y_{N}(\mathbf{0}) + G_{Nj}(\mathbf{0})[x_{j}] + \frac{1}{2}H_{Njk}(\mathbf{0})[x_{j},x_{k}] + \dots \end{pmatrix} \end{aligned} \end{equation}\] <p>This is the most general case and forms the mathematical foundation for inferring latent manifolds from data. Here, we have any number of latent variables describing any number of physical observables.</p> <h3 id="multilinear-forms">Multilinear Forms</h3> <p>For completeness, let’s also define the Maclaurin expansion of the $i$th element of a multivariate, vector–valued function with a notation more general than that previously used in this post:</p> \[\begin{equation} \begin{aligned}\label{eqn:taylor_general} \mathcal{T}[f_{i}]&amp;= \frac{1}{0!}f_{i}(\mathbf{0}) + \frac{1}{1!}G_{ij}(\mathbf{0})[x_{j}] + \frac{1}{2!}H_{ijk}(\mathbf{0})[x_{j},x_{k}] + \cdots~. \end{aligned} \end{equation}\] <p>The following table defines multilinear forms:</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th>Form</th> <th>Mapping</th> <th>Description</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td>$G$</td> <td>$X \to \mathbb{R}$</td> <td>Linear form</td> </tr> <tr> <td>$H$</td> <td>$X \times X \to \mathbb{R}$</td> <td>Bilinear form</td> </tr> <tr> <td>$F$</td> <td>$X^k \to \mathbb{R}$</td> <td>$k$–linear form</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>The structure of the inferred latent manifold parameterized by a Taylor series expansion has its polynomial nonlinear structure encoded by different multilinear forms: the linear form encodes linear structure (i.e., that underpinning the subspace inferred through PCA/POD); the quadratic form encodes quadratic structure (i.e., the quadratic structure of a quadratic manifold); and so on for $k$–linear forms and higher order structure.</p> <h2 id="posing-an-optimization-problem-to-parameterize-a-truncated-maclaurin-polynomial">Posing an Optimization Problem to Parameterize a Truncated Maclaurin Polynomial</h2> <p>Now we want to leverage the equation for a general Taylor series expansion when $(n\neq1, N\neq1)$ so that we can use it as a model for our underlying latent manifold. Doing so facilitates its use in an optimization problem for parameterizing the multilinear forms composing the Taylor polynomial. This optimization problem is the same one solved in PCA/POD, spectral submanifold, and polynomial manifold applications. Be aware that this subsection is rather mathy (as if this blog post wasn’t already).</p> <p>First, let $\mathbf{y}\in\mathbb{R}^N$ be a function of $\mathbf{x}\in\mathbb{R}^n$ and represent $\mathbf{y}$ in terms of its Maclaurin expansion. Notice that $\mathbf{y}:\mathbb{R}^N\rightarrow\mathbb{R}^n$, so $\mathbf{y}$ is a multivariate, vector–valued function, and thus permits a Maclaurin expansion:</p> \[\begin{equation} \begin{aligned}\label{eqn:start} \mathbf{y} = \begin{pmatrix} \mathcal{T}[y_{1}] \\ \mathcal{T}[y_{2}] \\ \vdots \\ \mathcal{T}[y_{N}] \end{pmatrix} &amp;= \begin{pmatrix} y_{1}(\mathbf{0}) + G_{1j}(\mathbf{0})[x_{j}] + \frac{1}{2}H_{1jk}(\mathbf{0})[x_{j},x_{k}] + \dots \\ y_{2}(\mathbf{0}) + G_{2j}(\mathbf{0})[x_{j}] + \frac{1}{2}H_{2jk}(\mathbf{0})[x_{j},x_{k}] + \dots \\ \vdots \\ y_{N}(\mathbf{0}) + G_{Nj}(\mathbf{0})[x_{j}] + \frac{1}{2}H_{Njk}(\mathbf{0})[x_{j},x_{k}] + \dots \end{pmatrix}\\ &amp;= \begin{pmatrix} y_{1}(\mathbf{0}) \\ y_{2}(\mathbf{0}) \\ \vdots \\ y_{N}(\mathbf{0}) \end{pmatrix} + \begin{pmatrix} G_{1j}(\mathbf{0})[x_{j}] \\ G_{2j}(\mathbf{0})[x_{j}] \\ \vdots \\ G_{Nj}(\mathbf{0})[x_{j}] \end{pmatrix} +\frac{1}{2} \begin{pmatrix} H_{1jk}(\mathbf{0})[x_{j},x_{k}] \\ H_{2jk}(\mathbf{0})[x_{j},x_{k}] \\ \vdots \\ H_{Njk}(\mathbf{0})[x_{j},x_{k}] \end{pmatrix} +\dots~.\notag \end{aligned} \end{equation}\] <p>We now subtract $f_{i}(\mathbf{0})$ from $\mathcal{T}[y_{i}]$, yielding $\mathcal{\tilde{T}}[y_{i}]$:</p> \[\begin{equation} \begin{aligned} \begin{pmatrix} \mathcal{T}[y_{1}]-y_{1}(\mathbf{0}) \\ \mathcal{T}[y_{2}]-y_{2}(\mathbf{0}) \\ \vdots \\ \mathcal{T}[y_{N}]-y_{N}(\mathbf{0}) \end{pmatrix} &amp;= \begin{pmatrix} \mathcal{\tilde{T}}[y_{1}] \\ \mathcal{\tilde{T}}[y_{2}] \\ \vdots \\ \mathcal{\tilde{T}}[y_{N}] \end{pmatrix} \\ &amp;= \begin{pmatrix} G_{1j}(\mathbf{0})[x_{j}] \\ G_{2j}(\mathbf{0})[x_{j}] \\ \vdots \\ G_{Nj}(\mathbf{0})[x_{j}] \end{pmatrix} +\frac{1}{2} \begin{pmatrix} H_{1jk}(\mathbf{0})[x_{j},x_{k}] \\ H_{2jk}(\mathbf{0})[x_{j},x_{k}] \\ \vdots \\ H_{Njk}(\mathbf{0})[x_{j},x_{k}] \end{pmatrix} +\dots~. \end{aligned} \end{equation}\] <p>To improve legibility, we define $\tilde{\mathbf{y}}$ as the corresponding vector of these $\mathcal{\tilde{T}}[y_{i}]$:</p> \[\begin{equation} \begin{aligned} \tilde{\mathbf{y}} = \begin{pmatrix} G_{1j}(\mathbf{0})[x_{j}] \\ G_{2j}(\mathbf{0})[x_{j}] \\ \vdots \\ G_{Nj}(\mathbf{0})[x_{j}] \end{pmatrix} +\frac{1}{2} \begin{pmatrix} H_{1jk}(\mathbf{0})[x_{j},x_{k}] \\ H_{2jk}(\mathbf{0})[x_{j},x_{k}] \\ \vdots \\ H_{Njk}(\mathbf{0})[x_{j},x_{k}] \end{pmatrix} +\dots~. \end{aligned} \end{equation}\] <p>Next, we “pull out” the arguments of the multilinear forms into their corresponding vectors of monomials. Here, $G_{i}(\mathbf{0};j)$ is a function parameterized by index $j$ corresponding to the $j$ in $x_{j}$ Likewise for $H_{i}(\mathbf{0};j,k)$ with indices $j$ and $k$ from product $x_{j}x_{k}$ and higher–order terms.</p> \[\begin{equation} \begin{aligned}\label{eqn:pull-out} \tilde{\mathbf{y}} = \begin{pmatrix} G_{1}(\mathbf{0};j) \\ G_{2}(\mathbf{0};j) \\ \vdots \\ G_{N}(\mathbf{0};j) \end{pmatrix} \begin{pmatrix} x_{1} \\ x_{2} \\ \vdots \\ x_{n} \end{pmatrix} + \begin{pmatrix} H_{1}(\mathbf{0};j,k) \\ H_{2}(\mathbf{0};j,k) \\ \vdots \\ H_{N}(\mathbf{0};j,k) \end{pmatrix} \begin{pmatrix} x_{1}^{2} \\ x_{1}x_{2} \\ x_{2}x_{1} \\ x_{1}x_{3} \\ \vdots \\ x_{n}x_{n-1} \\ x_{n}^{2} \end{pmatrix} +\dots~, \end{aligned} \end{equation}\] <p>where the factor of $1/2$ was absorbed into each $H_i(\mathbf{0};j,k)$.</p> <p>To better understand this equation, we now write out the elements of its matrix operators explicitly:</p> \[\begin{equation} \begin{aligned}\label{eqn:ytilde_matrices} \tilde{\mathbf{y}} &amp;= \begin{pmatrix} G_{1}(\mathbf{0};1) &amp; G_{1}(\mathbf{0};2) &amp; \dots &amp; G_{1}(\mathbf{0};n) \\ G_{2}(\mathbf{0};1) &amp; G_{2}(\mathbf{0};2) &amp; \dots &amp; G_{2}(\mathbf{0};n) \\ \vdots \\ G_{N}(\mathbf{0};1) &amp; G_{N}(\mathbf{0};2) &amp; \dots &amp; G_{N}(\mathbf{0};n) \\ \end{pmatrix} \begin{pmatrix} x_{1} \\ x_{2} \\ \vdots \\ x_{n} \end{pmatrix}+ \\&amp;+ \begin{pmatrix} H_{1}(\mathbf{0};1,1) &amp; H_{1}(\mathbf{0};1,2) &amp; H_{1}(\mathbf{0};2,1) &amp; H_{1}(\mathbf{0};2,2) &amp; \dots &amp; H_{1}(\mathbf{0};n,n-1) &amp; H_{1}(\mathbf{0};n,n)\\ H_{2}(\mathbf{0};1,1) &amp; H_{2}(\mathbf{0};1,2) &amp; H_{2}(\mathbf{0};2,1) &amp; H_{2}(\mathbf{0};2,2) &amp; \dots &amp; H_{2}(\mathbf{0};n,n-1) &amp; H_{2}(\mathbf{0};n,n) \\ \vdots \\ H_{N}(\mathbf{0};1,1) &amp; H_{N}(\mathbf{0};1,2) &amp; H_{N}(\mathbf{0};2,1) &amp; H_{1}(\mathbf{0};2,2) &amp; \dots &amp; H_{N}(\mathbf{0};n,n-1) &amp; H_{N}(\mathbf{0};n,n) \end{pmatrix} \begin{pmatrix} x_{1}^{2} \\ x_{1}x_{2} \\ x_{2}x_{1} \\ x_{1}x_{3} \\ \vdots \\ x_{n}x_{n-1} \\ x_{n}^{2} \end{pmatrix} +\dots~.\notag \end{aligned} \end{equation}\] <p>We can thus deduce the sizes of the respective matrix operators, where Kronecker product notation and matrices $\mathbf{T}_1$ and $\mathbf{T}_2$ have been leveraged for conciseness:</p> \[\begin{equation} \begin{aligned}\label{eqn:ytilde_sizes} \underbrace{ \tilde{\mathbf{y}} }_{ \mathbb{R}^{N\times 1} } &amp;= \underbrace{ \begin{pmatrix} G_{1}(\mathbf{0};j) \\ G_{2}(\mathbf{0};j) \\ \vdots \\ G_{N}(\mathbf{0};j) \end{pmatrix} }_{ \mathbb{R}^{N\times n} } \underbrace{ \mathbf{x} }_{ \mathbb{R}^{n\times 1} } + \underbrace{ \begin{pmatrix} H_{1}(\mathbf{0};j,k) \\ H_{2}(\mathbf{0};j,k) \\ \vdots \\ H_{N}(\mathbf{0};j,k) \end{pmatrix} }_{ \mathbb{R}^{N\times n^{2}} } \underbrace{ \mathbf{x}\otimes\mathbf{x} }_{ \mathbb{R}^{n^{2}\times 1} } +\dots\\ &amp;=\mathbf{T}_1\mathbf{x} + \mathbf{T}_2\mathbf{x}\otimes\mathbf{x}+\dots\notag~. \end{aligned} \end{equation}\] <p>So far we have considered an infinite series Maclaurin expansion. Let us now consider the following truncated expansion, yielding a quadratic approximation of $\tilde{\mathbf{y}}$:</p> \[\begin{equation} \begin{aligned}\label{eqn:truncated} \tilde{\mathbf{y}} \approx \mathbf{T}_1\mathbf{x} + \mathbf{T}_2\mathbf{x}\otimes\mathbf{x}. \end{aligned} \end{equation}\] <p>This truncation is necessary since our end goal is to solve a problem on a computer, so we cannot infer an infinite amount of terms. However, it does not mean that our results won’t be accurate, as truncations such that the largest $d$ is $1$ are common—they, in fact, formulate linear PCA/POD!</p> <p>Assuming that we have access to numerical data sufficiently describing $\tilde{\mathbf{y}}$ and $\mathbf{x}$, we can thus pose the following least–squares optimization problem to infer the values of $G_{i}(\mathbf{0};j)$ and $H_{i}(\mathbf{0};j,k)$ where $i\in { 1,2,\dots,N }$ and $j,k\in{1,2,\dots,n}$:</p> \[\begin{equation} \begin{aligned} \text{argmin}_{\mathbf{T}_1,\mathbf{T}_2} \left\lVert \tilde{\mathbf{y}} - \mathbf{T}_1\mathbf{x} - \mathbf{T}_2\mathbf{x}\otimes\mathbf{x} \right\rVert_2^2. \end{aligned} \end{equation}\] <p>Of course, we could generalize this optimization problem to include monomial terms in our Kronecker product vectors up to degree $d$, yielding the following problem:</p> \[\begin{equation} \begin{aligned}\label{eqn:result} \text{argmin}_{\{ \mathbf{T}_{p} \}} \left\lVert \tilde{\mathbf{y}} - \sum_{p=1}^d\mathbf{T}_p\mathbf{x}^{\otimes p} \right\rVert_2^2. \end{aligned} \end{equation}\] <p>Finally, we can assume that $\mathbf{T}_p=\mathbf{V}_p\mathbf{R}_p$, where $\mathbf{Q}_p\in\mathbb{R}^{N\times n^p}$ is orthogonal and $\mathbf{R}_p\in\mathbb{R}^{n^p\times n^p}$ is upper–triangular. Using this QR decomposition, we can rewrite our truncated expansion using orthogonal matrices, where $\mathbf{s}^{\otimes p}\equiv\mathbf{R}_p\mathbf{x}^{\otimes p}$:</p> \[\begin{equation} \begin{aligned}\label{eqn:result_with_orthogonal_matrices} \text{argmin}_{\{ \mathbf{V}_{p} \}} \left\lVert \tilde{\mathbf{y}} - \sum_{p=1}^d\mathbf{V}_p\mathbf{s}^{\otimes p} \right\rVert_2^2. \end{aligned} \end{equation}\] <h2 id="sequential-closure-modeling">Sequential Closure Modeling</h2> <p>One way to solve for decoders ${\mathbf{V}_1, \mathbf{V}_2, \dots, \mathbf{V}_d}$ is to do so sequentially: using reconstruction error with respect to decoders ${\mathbf{V}_1, \dots, \mathbf{V}_{p-1}}$ to formulate a linear least–squares optimization problem for inferring decoder $\mathbf{V}_p$.</p> <h3 id="inferring-mathbfv_1">Inferring $\mathbf{V}_1$</h3> <p>To begin our sequential optimization we must infer our linear decoder $\mathbf{V}_1$. The optimization for $\mathbf{V}_1$ is as follows</p> \[\begin{equation} \begin{aligned}\label{eqn:V1_min_problem} \mathbf{V}_1 = \text{argmin}\frac{1}{2}\lVert \mathbf{V}_1^\top \mathbf{S} - \hat{\mathbf{\mathbf{S}}} \rVert_\text{F}^2. \end{aligned} \end{equation}\] <p>The solution to this least–squares problem is given by the matrix of POD basis vectors obtained through the SVD.</p> <p>With linear decoder $\mathbf{V}_1$ now in hand we can compute the reconstruction error associated with it, $\mathcal{E}_1$:</p> \[\begin{equation} \begin{aligned}\label{eqn:err_after_linear} \mathcal{E}_1&amp;=(\mathbf{I}-\mathbf{V}_1\mathbf{V}_1^\top)\mathbf{S}\nonumber\\ &amp;= [\tilde{\mathbf{V}}_1][\tilde{\mathbf{V}}_1]^\top \mathbf{S}. \end{aligned} \end{equation}\] <p>This reconstruction error with respect to $\mathbf{V}_1$ can then be used as the basis to infer $\mathbf{V}_2$.</p> <h3 id="inferring-mathbfv_2">Inferring $\mathbf{V}_2$</h3> <p>We can leverage $\mathcal{E}_1$ to formulate an optimization problem for $\mathbf{V}_2$ such that it best fixes the error left over from $\mathbf{V}_1$. This is written out in the following equation, where $\mathbf{W}_2=\mathbf{S}^{\diamond 2} = \mathbf{S}\diamond\mathbf{S}=\begin{pmatrix} \mathbf{s}_1\otimes\mathbf{s}_1 \dots \mathbf{s}_K\otimes \mathbf{s}_K \end{pmatrix}$ is the second Khatri–Rao power of $\mathbf{S}$, storing all quadratic snapshot monomials of all snapshots:</p> \[\begin{equation} \begin{aligned}\label{eqn:V2_min_problem} \mathbf{V}_2 = \text{argmin}\frac{1}{2}\lVert W_2^\top \mathbf{V}_2^\top - \mathcal{E}_1^\top \rVert_\text{F}^2 \end{aligned} \end{equation}\] <p>Computing $\mathbf{V}_2$ as the quadratic decoder that best–closes the linear model parameterized by $\mathbf{V}_1$ establishes that $\mathbf{V}_2\perp\mathbf{V}_1$. We will now derive this.</p> <p>First we define the loss function, $J$, that we intend to optimize. For optimizing $\mathbf{V}_2$ through our sequential optimization framework, $J=J(\mathbf{V}_2)$. We are seeking the least–squares solution and thus obtain the following loss function:</p> \[\begin{equation} \begin{aligned}\label{eqn:V2_cost_function} J(\mathbf{V}_{2}) &amp;= \frac{1}{2}\lVert \mathbf{W}_{2}^{\top}\mathbf{V}_{2}^{\top}-\mathcal{E}_{1}^{\top} \rVert_\text{F}^2, \end{aligned} \end{equation}\] <p>where the factor of $1/2$ in front of the Frobenius norm exists to simplify the arithmetic encountered in matrix calculus–based optimization.</p> <p>With an equation for $J(\mathbf{V}_{2})$ in hand we can put it into an equivalent but more suitable form for optimization by taking advantage of the trace operator, $\text{tr}$, as done as follows:</p> \[\begin{equation} \begin{aligned}\label{eqn:V2_cost_function_trace} \frac{1}{2}\lVert \mathbf{W}_{2}^{\top}\mathbf{V}_{2}^{\top}-\mathcal{E}_{1}^{\top} \rVert_\text{F}^2 &amp;= \frac{1}{2}\text{tr}\left( \left( \mathbf{W}_{2}^{\top}\mathbf{V}_{2}^{\top}-\mathcal{E}_{1}^{\top} \right)^{\top} \left( \mathbf{W}_{2}^{\top}\mathbf{V}_{2}^{\top}-\mathcal{E}_{1}^{\top} \right) \right) \nonumber\\ &amp;=\frac{1}{2}\text{tr} \left( \left( \mathbf{V}_{2}\mathbf{W}_{2}-\mathcal{E}_{1} \right) \left( \mathbf{W}_{2}^{\top}\mathbf{V}_{2}^{\top}-\mathcal{E}_{1}^{\top} \right) \right) \nonumber \\ &amp;= \frac{1}{2}\text{tr}\left( \mathbf{V}_{2}\mathbf{W}_{2}\mathbf{W}_{2}^{\top}\mathbf{V}_{2}^{\top} - \mathbf{V}_{2}\mathbf{W}_{2}\mathcal{E}_{1}^{\top} - \mathcal{E}_{1}\mathbf{W}_{2}^{\top}\mathbf{V}_{2}^{\top} + \mathcal{E}_{1}\mathcal{E}_{1}^{\top} \right) \nonumber \\ &amp;= \frac{1}{2}\text{tr}\left( \mathbf{V}_{2}\mathbf{W}_{2}\mathbf{W}_{2}^{\top}\mathbf{V}_{2}^{\top} \right) - \text{tr}\left( \mathbf{V}_{2}\mathbf{W}_{2}\mathcal{E}_{1}^{\top} \right) + \frac{1}{2}\text{tr}\left( \mathcal{E}_{1}\mathcal{E}_{1}^{\top} \right) \end{aligned} \end{equation}\] <p>Our goal is to minimize the loss function $J(\mathbf{V}_2)$ with respect to the variable $\mathbf{V}_2$, so we will now compute the gradient of $J(\mathbf{V}_2)$ with respect to $\mathbf{V}_2$:</p> \[\begin{equation} \begin{aligned}\label{eqn:V2_gradient} \nabla_{\mathbf{V}_{2}}J(\mathbf{V}_{2}) &amp;= \frac{1}{2}\nabla_{\mathbf{V}_{2}}\left( \mathbf{V}_{2}\mathbf{W}_{2}\mathbf{W}_{2}^{\top}\mathbf{V}_{2}^{\top} \right) - \nabla_{\mathbf{V}_{2}}\left( \mathbf{V}_{2}\mathbf{W}_{2}\mathcal{E}_{1}^{\top} \right) \\ &amp;\quad + \cancel{ \frac{1}{2}\nabla_{\mathbf{V}_{2}}\text{tr}\left( \left( \mathbf{I}-\mathbf{V}_{1}\mathbf{V}_{1}^{\top} \right) S_{1}S_{1}^{\top}\left( \mathbf{I}-\mathbf{V}_{1}\mathbf{V}_{1}^{\top} \right) \right) } \nonumber \\ &amp;= \mathbf{W}_{2}\mathbf{W}_{2}^{\top}\mathbf{V}_{2}^{\top} - \mathbf{W}_{2}\mathcal{E}_{1}^{\top}, \end{aligned} \end{equation}\] <p>where we can see that including the factor of $1/2$ in $J(\mathbf{V}<em>{2})$ allows us to have no non–unity scalars in our expression of the gradient in the equation for $\nabla</em>{\mathbf{V}<em>{2}}J(\mathbf{V}</em>{2})$.</p> <p>Now that we have $\nabla_{\mathbf{V}<em>{2}}J(\mathbf{V}</em>{2})$ we can force it to be $0$ so that we identify a root of $\nabla_{\mathbf{V}_2}J(\mathbf{V}_2)$ and thus an extremum of $J(\mathbf{V}_2)$:</p> \[\begin{equation} \begin{aligned}\label{eqn:V2_optimization_via_gradient} \nabla_{\mathbf{V}_{2}}J(\mathbf{V}_{2}) \overset{!}{=} 0 \implies \mathbf{W}_{2}\mathbf{W}_{2}^{\top}\mathbf{V}_{2}^{\top} - \mathbf{W}_{2}\mathcal{E}_{1}^{\top} = 0, \end{aligned} \end{equation}\] <p>where $\overset{!}{=}$ notation is used since we are forcing $\nabla_{\mathbf{V}_2}J(\mathbf{V}_2)$ to equal $0$ for optimization purposes.</p> <p>Finally, we can solve for $\mathbf{V}_2$ to show that $\mathbf{V}_2\perp\mathbf{V}_1$:</p> \[\begin{equation} \begin{aligned}\label{eqn:V2_orthogonal_to_V1} \mathbf{V}_{2}^{\top} &amp;= \left(\mathbf{W}_{2}\mathbf{W}_{2}^{\top}\right)^{-1}\mathbf{W}_{2}\mathcal{E}_{1}^{\top} \nonumber \\ \mathbf{V}_{2} &amp;= \mathcal{E}_{1}\mathbf{W}_{2}^{\top}\left( \mathbf{W}_{2}\mathbf{W}_{2}^{\top} \right)^{-1} \nonumber \\ &amp;= (\mathbf{I}-\mathbf{V}_{1}\mathbf{V}_{1}^{\top}) \mathbf{S}\mathbf{W}_{2}^{\top}\left( \mathbf{W}_{2}\mathbf{W}_{2}^{\top} \right)^{-1}\nonumber \\ &amp;= \tilde{\mathbf{V}}_{1}\tilde{\mathbf{V}}_{1}^{\top}\left( \mathbf{S} \mathbf{W}_{2}^{\top}\left( \mathbf{W}_{2}\mathbf{W}_{2}^{\top} \right)^{-1} \right), \end{aligned} \end{equation}\] <p>where $\tilde{\mathbf{V}}_1\tilde{\mathbf{V}}_1^\top$ is an orthogonal projector onto the orthogonal complement of $\mathbf{V}_1$. Therefore, $\mathbf{V}_2\perp \mathbf{V}_1$.</p> <p>Additionally, we can compute the reconstruction error after leveraging both the linear and quadratic decoder, $\mathcal{E}_2$:</p> \[\begin{equation} \begin{aligned}\label{eqn:err_after_quadratic} \mathcal{E}_{2} &amp;= \left( \mathbf{I}-\mathbf{V}_{1}\mathbf{V}_{1}^{\top}-\mathbf{V}_{2}\mathbf{V}_{2}^{\top} \right) \mathbf{S} \nonumber\\ &amp;= \left[ \tilde{\mathbf{V}}_{1} \tilde{\mathbf{V}}_{2} \right] \left[ \tilde{\mathbf{V}}_{1} \tilde{\mathbf{V}}_{2} \right]^{\top} \mathbf{S}. \end{aligned} \end{equation}\] <p>Our goal so far, however, is to infer the $\mathbf{V}_2$ that minimizes its given loss function. Since the optimization problem is a linear least–squares problem, we can solve it with the QR decomposition as follows:</p> \[\begin{equation} \begin{aligned}\label{eqn:V2_least_squares} \mathbf{V}_{2}\mathbf{W}_{2}\mathbf{W}_{2}^{\top} &amp;= \mathcal{E}_{1}\mathbf{W}_{2}^{\top}\nonumber \\ \mathbf{V}_{2}\left( \mathbf{Q}_{2}\mathbf{R}_{2} \right)^{\top}\left( \mathbf{Q}_{2}\mathbf{R}_{2} \right) &amp;= \mathcal{E}_{1}(\mathbf{Q}_{2}\mathbf{R}_{2}) \nonumber\\ \mathbf{V}_{2}\mathbf{R}_{2}^{\top}\mathbf{R}_{2} &amp;= \mathcal{E}_{1}\mathbf{Q}_{2}\mathbf{R}_{2} \nonumber\\ \mathbf{V}_{2}\mathbf{R}_{2}^{\top} &amp;= \underbrace{ \mathcal{E}_{1}\mathbf{Q}_{2} }_{ \mathbf{Y}_{2} } \nonumber\\ \mathbf{R}_{2}\mathbf{V}_{2}^{\top} &amp;= \mathbf{Y}_{2}^{\top}. \end{aligned} \end{equation}\] <h3 id="inferring-mathbfv_3">Inferring $\mathbf{V}_3$</h3> <p>The cubic decoder $\mathbf{V_3}$ can be inferred as the matrix that best–fixes the quadratic reconstruction error by solving the following optimization problem:</p> \[\begin{equation} \begin{aligned} \mathbf{V}_{3}=\text{argmin}\frac{1}{2}\lVert \mathbf{W}_{3}^{\top}\mathbf{V}_{3}^{\top}-\mathcal{E}_{2}^{\top} \rVert_\text{F}^2, \end{aligned} \end{equation}\] <p>where $\mathbf{W}_3 = \mathbf{S}^{\diamond3} = \mathbf{S}\diamond \mathbf{S}\diamond \mathbf{S} = (\mathbf{s}_1\otimes\mathbf{s}_1\otimes\mathbf{s}_1\dots\mathbf{s}_K\otimes\mathbf{s}_K\otimes\mathbf{s}_K)$ is the third Khatri–Rao power of $\mathbf{S}$ that stores all cubic monomial terms of all snapshots.</p> <p>We can prove that $\mathbf{V}_3$ is orthogonal to both $\mathbf{V_1}$ and $\mathbf{V_2}$:</p> \[\begin{equation} \begin{aligned} \mathbf{V}_{3} &amp;= \mathcal{E}_{2}\mathbf{W}_{3}^{\top}\left( \mathbf{W}_{3}\mathbf{W}_{3}^{\top} \right)^{-1} \nonumber\\ &amp;= \left( \mathbf{I}- \mathbf{V}_{1}\mathbf{V}_{1}^{\top} - \mathbf{V}_{2}\mathbf{V}_{2}^{\top} \right)\mathbf{S}\mathbf{W}_{3}^{\top}\left( \mathbf{W}_{3}\mathbf{W}_{3}^{\top} \right)^{-1} \nonumber\\ &amp;= \left[ \tilde{\mathbf{V}}_{1} \tilde{\mathbf{V}}_{2} \right] \left[ \tilde{\mathbf{V}}_{1} \tilde{\mathbf{V}}_{2} \right]^{\top} \left( \mathbf{S}\mathbf{W}_{3}^{\top}\left( \mathbf{W}_{3}\mathbf{W}_{3}^{\top} \right)^{-1} \right) \end{aligned} \end{equation}\] <p>where $\left[ \tilde{\mathbf{V}}<em>{1} \tilde{\mathbf{V}}</em>{2} \right] \left[ \tilde{\mathbf{V}}<em>{1} \tilde{\mathbf{V}}</em>{2} \right]^{\top}$ is a projector onto the orthogonal complement of $\text{span}{ \mathbf{v}^{(1)}_1, \dots, \mathbf{v}^{(n)}_1, \mathbf{v}^{(1)}_2, \dots, \mathbf{v}^{(n^2)}_1 }$. Therefore, $\mathbf{V}_3\perp {\mathbf{V}_1, \mathbf{V}_2}$.</p> <p>Additionally, we can identify a closed–form solution to the least–squares problem for $\mathbf{V}_3$ using the QR decomposition:</p> \[\begin{equation} \begin{aligned}\label{eqn:V3_least_squares} \mathbf{V}_{3}\mathbf{W}_{3}\mathbf{W}_{3}^{\top} &amp;= \mathcal{E}_{2}\mathbf{W}_{3}^{\top} \nonumber\\ \mathbf{V}_{3}\left( \mathbf{Q}_{3}\mathbf{R}_{3} \right)^{\top}\left( \mathbf{Q}_{3}\mathbf{R}_{3} \right) &amp;= \mathcal{E}_{2}(\mathbf{Q}_{3}\mathbf{R}_{3}) \nonumber\\ \mathbf{V}_{3}\mathbf{R}_{3}^{\top}\mathbf{R}_{3} &amp;= \mathcal{E}_{2}\mathbf{Q}_{3}\mathbf{R}_{3}\nonumber \\ \mathbf{V}_{3}\mathbf{R}_{3}^{\top} &amp;= \underbrace{ \mathcal{E}_{2}\mathbf{Q}_{3} }_{ \mathbf{Y}_{3} } \nonumber\\ \mathbf{R}_{3}\mathbf{V}_{3}^{\top} &amp;= \mathbf{Y}_{3}^{\top}. \end{aligned} \end{equation}\] <h3 id="inferring-mathbfv_k1">Inferring $\mathbf{V}_{k+1}$</h3> <p>Finally, we may apply logic analogous to that used to derive $\mathbf{V}<em>2$ from $\mathbf{V}_1$ and $\mathbf{V_3}$ from ${\mathbf{V_1},\mathbf{V_2}}$ in order to derive $\mathbf{V}</em>{k+1}$ from ${\mathbf{V}<em>k}</em>{k=1}^d$.</p> <p>We begin by posing the following least–squares problem for $\mathbf{V}_{k+1}$:</p> \[\begin{equation} \begin{aligned} \mathbf{V}_{k+1} = \text{argmin}\frac{1}{2}\lVert \mathbf{W}_{k+1}^{\top}\mathbf{V}_{k+1}^{\top}-\mathcal{E}_{k}^{\top} \rVert_{\text{F}}^2, \end{aligned} \end{equation}\] <p>where $\mathbf{W}<em>{k+1}=\mathbf{S}^{\diamond(k+1)}$ is the $(k+1)$th Khatri–Rao power of $\mathbf{S}$ and $\mathcal{E}_k$ is the reconstruction error with respect to decoders ${ \mathbf{V}_p }</em>{p=1}^{k}$.</p> <p>Next, we can prove that decoder $\mathbf{V}<em>{k+1}$ is orthogonal to ${ \mathbf{V}_1, \dots,\mathbf{V}</em>{k}}$:</p> \[\begin{equation} \begin{aligned} \mathbf{V}_{k+1} &amp;= \mathcal{E}_{k}\mathbf{W}_{k+1}^{\top}\left( \mathbf{W}_{k+1}\mathbf{W}_{k+1}^{\top} \right)^{-1}\nonumber \\ &amp;= \left( \mathbf{I}- \sum_{i=1}^{k}\mathbf{V}_{i}\mathbf{V}_{i}^{\top} \right) \mathbf{S} \mathbf{W}_{k+1}^{\top}\left( \mathbf{W}_{k+1}\mathbf{W}_{k+1}^{\top} \right)^{-1} \nonumber \\ &amp;= \left[ \tilde{\mathbf{V}}_{1} \tilde{\mathbf{V}}_{2} \dots \tilde{\mathbf{V}}_{k} \right] \left[ \tilde{\mathbf{V}}_{1} \tilde{\mathbf{V}}_{2} \dots \tilde{\mathbf{V}}_{k} \right]^{\top} \left(\mathbf{S} \mathbf{W}_{k+1}^{\top}\left( \mathbf{W}_{k+1}\mathbf{W}_{k+1}^{\top} \right)^{-1} \right), \end{aligned} \end{equation}\] <p>such that $\mathbf{V}_{k+1}\perp { \mathbf{V}_1,\mathbf{V}_2,\dots,\mathbf{V}_k }$.</p> <p>Lastly, we can solve a system of linear equations to infer $\mathbf{V}_{k+1}$, where the derivation is analogous to those used to derive expressions for $\mathbf{V}_1$ and $\mathbf{V}_2$:</p> \[\begin{equation} \begin{aligned} \mathbf{R}_{k+1}\mathbf{V}_{k+1}^{\top} = \mathbf{Y}_{k+1}^\top. \end{aligned} \end{equation}\] <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2> <p>In this post we have showed how to solve an optimization problem from data to infer latent manifolds modeled by truncated Taylor series expansions. Such manifolds form the basis of polynomial manifolds and spectral submanifolds used in model order reduction. In fact, Justin suspects that they are different names of the same optimization result.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="numerical-methods"/><category term="ML"/><category term="optimization"/><category term="dimensionality-reduction"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[TODO figures, simpler wording, less mathematically overwhelming, proofreading]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Physics–Informed Source Separation</title><link href="https://jburz2001.github.io/blog/2025/jax-for-physics-informed-source-separation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Physics–Informed Source Separation"/><published>2025-11-13T14:14:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-11-13T14:14:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jburz2001.github.io/blog/2025/jax-for-physics-informed-source-separation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jburz2001.github.io/blog/2025/jax-for-physics-informed-source-separation/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="source-separation-from-smoothies-to-pdes">Source Separation: From Smoothies to PDEs</h2> <p>Physical systems are often measured as mixtures of signals. For instance, seismometers measure not only the magnitude of earthquakes but also any other vibrations significant enough to register, such as mining explosions. Such extraneous signals can corrupt measurements (e.g., pressure waves from mining explosions mixed with seismic pressure waves from earthquakes), so it is often vital to isolate the signals of interest. This process is called source separation and is a type of inverse problem since the goal is to infer the original source signals (i.e., causes) from a collection of observed mixtures (i.e., effects). Source separation problems are often blind due to the absence of a well–defined model for how the constituent signals were mixed or of the sources themselves.</p> <p>As an analogy for blind source separation, imagine if I concocted a delicious smoothie and tasked you with reverse engineering the recipe! With training, you can become better at deconstructing the smoothie by incorporating knowledge of how smoothies are typically made, how Justin likes to make smoothies, which ingredients are reasonable for smoothies, etc. This accumulated knowledge of “smoothie deconstruction” can be thought of in a statistical sense as <em>a priori</em> information. One could take this analogy further by assuming that this <em>a priori</em> information represents a Bayesian prior that updates over time with each taste test! Training a machine learning model with this <em>a priori</em> information would be an instance of “smoothie–informed machine learning.”</p> <p>Fortunately, unlike smoothies, many physical systems yield observed signals whose constituent mixed sources abide by known partial differential equations (PDEs), such as the linear advection equation. This information can be leveraged as <em>a priori</em> information, yielding physics–informed source separation algorithms with improved efficiency, accuracy, and mathematical well–posedness.</p> <p>This post elaborates on these points by explaining:</p> <ul> <li>An example blind source separation (BSS) problem from physics</li> <li>How to regularize the aforementioned BSS problem with physically meaningful loss terms that incorporate <em>a priori</em> information about the constituent source signals</li> <li>The penalty method for converting numerical constrained optimization problems into unconstrained ones</li> <li>The method of multipliers for improving convergence of the penalty method</li> <li>The Gauss–Newton algorithm and Levenberg–Marquardt algorithm for solving nonlinear least–squares problems</li> <li>Implementation in Python using NumPy, JAX, and JAXopt libraries for high–performance computing–based numerical simulation of PDEs and optimization.</li> </ul> <h2 id="the-linear-advection-pde">The Linear Advection PDE</h2> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posts/physics-informed-source-separation/U1_true-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/posts/physics-informed-source-separation/U1_true-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/posts/physics-informed-source-separation/U1_true-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/physics-informed-source-separation/U1_true.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posts/physics-informed-source-separation/U_sum_true-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/posts/physics-informed-source-separation/U_sum_true-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/posts/physics-informed-source-separation/U_sum_true-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/physics-informed-source-separation/U_sum_true.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posts/physics-informed-source-separation/U2_true-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/posts/physics-informed-source-separation/U2_true-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/posts/physics-informed-source-separation/U2_true-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/physics-informed-source-separation/U2_true.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Click on an image to enlarge it. <strong>Left:</strong> Simulated true source one. <strong>Middle:</strong> Simulated true source one + true source two. <strong>Right:</strong> Simulated true source two. This article explains how to extract the data in the left and right images from the middle image. </div> <p>Physics is often expressed in the language of partial differential equations (PDEs). These equations leverage partial derivatives to model how multivariate dependent variables respond to changes in their independent variables, often space and time. For instance, the linear advection equation models how the value of an advected quantity changes according to the spatial gradient of that quantity and the underlying velocity field. The algebraic structure of this PDE and the spectral properties of the differential operators composing it conspire together to model translational motion called advection.</p> <p>This post uses JAX for physics–informed source separation with simulated data from a 1–dimensional linear advection PDE. This equation is linear, ubiquitous, and well–suited to modeling the transport of localized signals that are easily distinguished by the naked eye but not necessarily to a <em>blind</em> source separation algorithm. Linearity of the advection equation is particularly helpful here since it allows us to easily model the (trivially) coupled evolution of multiple advecting signals by virtue of the principle of superposition:</p> \[\begin{equation} \frac{\partial(\sum_{i=1}^{n}u_i)}{\partial t} + \frac{\partial (\sum_{i=1}^{n}c_i u_i)}{\partial x} = 0 = \sum_{i=1}^{n}(\frac{\partial u_i}{\partial t} + \frac{\partial (c_i u_i)}{\partial x}), \end{equation}\] <p>where $u = \sum_{i=1}^{n}u_i$ is the observed signal and $f = \sum_{i=1}^{n}c_i u_i$ is the total flux.</p> <p>The rest of this post will assume that there are only two advecting pulses, yielding the following model of the observed flow field:</p> \[\begin{equation} \sum_{i=1}^{2}(\frac{\partial u_i}{\partial t} + \frac{\partial (c_i u_i)}{\partial x})=0, \end{equation}\] <p>where $c_i$ are constants quantifying advection speed. In general, determining the optimal value of $n$ (i.e., the number of sources being mixed) may not be trivial. However, there are plenty of data–driven methods to accomplish this. For instance, one could apply the line Hough transform to the Minkowski spacetime diagram of the observed solution then compute the number of disjoint maxima in this Hough space.</p> <h2 id="constrained-optimization-for-physicsinformed-source-separation">Constrained Optimization for Physics–Informed Source Separation</h2> <p>Recall that our observed signal is the superposition of multiple individually advecting signals. As such, we can pose the following BSS problem:</p> \[\begin{equation} (\hat{U}_1, \hat{U}_2) \in \arg\min_{U_1,U_2}\frac{1}{2} \left\lVert U_1 + U_2 - U \right\rVert_\text{F}^2, \end{equation}\] <p>where $U_1\in\mathbb{R}^{n\times K}$ is a matrix whose $j$th column is source one at timestamp $j$, $u_1(:, t_j)$; $U_2\in\mathbb{R}^{n\times K}$ is a matrix whose $j$th column is source two at timestamp $j$, $u_2(:, t_j)$; and $U\in\mathbb{R}^{n\times K}$ is a matrix whose $j$th column is the observed signal at timestamp $j$, $u(:, t_j)$. The $1/2$ in front of the Frobenius norm is a fudge factor used to remove irrelevant coefficients of $2$ from gradients of the norm with respect to design variables $U_1$, $U_2$, or $W=[U_1^\top \quad U_2^\top]^\top$ where $U_1 + U_2 - U = [I \quad I]~W - U$. Neglecting this $1/2$ does not change the optimal $(\hat{U}_1,\hat{U}_2)$.</p> <p>This BSS problem is unfortunately ill–posed since there are many equivalently–optimal solutions, most of which are physically meaningless. For instance, both $(\hat{U}_1,\hat{U}_2)=(U,0)$ and $(\hat{U}_1,\hat{U}_2)=(0,U)$ are valid solutions even though we assume $U_1\neq0\neq U_2$ by formulation of the residual in the norm being minimized. This ill–posedness is a common obstacle in the solution of computational inverse problems, such as source separation. Fortunately, <em>a priori</em> knowledge of signals $U_1$ and $U_2$ can be leveraged to regularize this problem, making it well–posed. One such regularization enforces that $\hat{U}_1$ and $\hat{U}_2$ are non–negative matrices:</p> \[\begin{equation} (\hat{U}_1, \hat{U}_2) \in \arg\min_{U_1\geq 0,U_2\geq 0}\frac{1}{2} \left\lVert U_1 + U_2 - U \right\rVert_\text{F}^2. \end{equation}\] <p>Additionally, we can assume that $U_1$ and $U_2$ satisfy their own advection equations:</p> \[\begin{equation} \begin{aligned} (\hat{U}_1, \hat{U}_2) &amp;\in \arg\min_{U_1 \ge 0,\, U_2 \ge 0} \Bigg[ \frac{1}{2}\,\| U_1 + U_2 - U \|_\text{F}^2 \\ &amp;\quad +\ \lambda_{\text{PDE}_1}\, \| \dot{U}_1 + c_1 U_1' \|_\text{F}^2 \\ &amp;\quad +\ \lambda_{\text{PDE}_2}\, \| \dot{U}_2 + c_2 U_2' \|_\text{F}^2 \Bigg], \end{aligned} \end{equation}\] <p>where $\dot{U}_i$ is a finite–difference–computed time derivative of $U_i$ and $U^\prime_i$ is a finite–difference–computed spatial derivative. Constants $c_i$ can be computed from observed snapshots $U$, such as from the slope of the $i$th line detected in Hough space via the line Hough transform of $U$.</p> <h2 id="unconstrained-optimization-for-physicsinformed-source-separation">Unconstrained Optimization for Physics–Informed Source Separation</h2> <p>Our constrained optimization problem can be converted into an unconstrained one through the penalty method. Doing so enables the solution of our constrained optimization problem by using optimizers for unconstrained problems:</p> \[\begin{equation} \begin{aligned} (\hat{U}_1^{(k)}, \hat{U}_2^{(k)}) &amp;\in \arg\min_{U_1^{(k)},\, U_2^{(k)}} \Bigg[ \frac{1}{2}\,\| U_1^{(k)} + U_2^{(k)} - U \|_\text{F}^2 \\ &amp;\quad +\ \lambda_{\text{PDE}_1}\, \| \dot{U}^{(k)}_1 + c_1 U^{(k)\prime}_1 \|_\text{F}^2 \\ &amp;\quad +\ \lambda_{\text{PDE}_2}\, \| \dot{U}^{(k)}_2 + c_2 U^{(k)\prime}_2 \|_\text{F}^2 \\ &amp;\quad +\ \frac{1}{2}\mu^{(k)} \big( \| \min(0,\,-U_1^{(k)}) \|_\text{F}^2 +\ \| \min(0,\,-U_2^{(k)}) \|_\text{F}^2 \big) \Bigg], \end{aligned} \end{equation}\] <p>where $\min$ is a function that computes the elementwise minimum of a matrix with the zero matrix of the same shape, thus penalizing negative values. Index $k$ is used to convey the $k$th iteration of the penalty method. In practice, one often starts the optimization procedure using a small value of $\mu^{(k)}$; obtains $(\hat{U}_1^{(k)}, \hat{U}_2^{(k)})$; then recursively solves for $(\hat{U}_1^{(k+1)}, \hat{U}_2^{(k+1)})$ until convergence using $\mu^{(k+1)} &gt; \mu^{(k)}$, where $(\hat{U}_1^{(k)}, \hat{U}_2^{(k)})$ is the initial guess of $(\hat{U}_1^{(k+1)}, \hat{U}_2^{(k+1)})$.</p> <p>Furthermore, we can express this least–squares problem’s objective function to be minimized using a single norm:</p> \[\begin{equation} \begin{aligned} (\hat{U}_1^{(k)}, \hat{U}_2^{(k)}) &amp;\in \arg\min_{U_1^{(k)},\, U_2^{(k)}} \frac{1}{2} \left\lVert \begin{bmatrix} U_1^{(k)} + U_2^{(k)} - U \\[6pt] \sqrt{2\lambda_{\text{PDE}_1}}\;\big(\dot{U}^{(k)}_1 + c_1\, U_1^{(k)\prime}\big) \\[6pt] \sqrt{2\lambda_{\text{PDE}_2}}\;\big(\dot{U}^{(k)}_2 + c_2\, U_2^{(k)\prime}\big) \\[6pt] \sqrt{\mu^{(k)}}\,\min(0,\,-U_1^{(k)}) \\[6pt] \sqrt{\mu^{(k)}}\,\min(0,\,-U_2^{(k)}) \end{bmatrix} \right\rVert_F^{\!2} \\[10pt] &amp;= \arg\min_{U_1^{(k)},\, U_2^{(k)}} \frac{1}{2}\,\| r^{(k)} \|_\text{F}^2, \end{aligned} \end{equation}\] <p>where $r^{(k)}$ is a single residual formed by stacking all constituent residuals in our objective function into a column vector. This notation with $r^{(k)}$ will facilitate the later use of the Levenberg–Marquardt algorithm for numerical optimization.</p> <h2 id="augmenting-the-penalty-method-with-lagrange-multipliers">Augmenting the Penalty Method With Lagrange Multipliers</h2> <p>Recall that we previously converted a constrained optimization problem into an unconstrained one using the penalty method. Intuitively, one recovers the constrained optimization solution in the limit as the penalty term, $\mu^{(k)}$, introduced by the penalty method, goes to infinity. Unfortunately, naively increasing $\mu^{(k)}$ towards infinity can make this optimization problem ill–posed if $\mu^{(k)}$ gets too large. However, one can circumvent the need to increase $\mu^{(k)}$ towards infinity by leveraging the method of multipliers (aka, the augmented Lagrangian method). The method of multipliers is analogous to the method of Lagrange multipliers from analytical optimization theory and forms the foundation of a standard tool in numerical optimization called the alternating direction method of multipliers, which is not covered in this post.</p> <p>The following equation represents the penalty method objective augmented with Lagrange multipliers:</p> \[\begin{equation} \begin{aligned} (\hat{U}_1^{(k)}, \hat{U}_2^{(k)}) \in &amp;\;\arg\min_{U_1^{(k)},\, U_2^{(k)}} \Bigg[ \frac{1}{2}\, \bigl\lVert r^{(k)} \bigr\rVert_F^2 \\ &amp;\qquad + \big\langle \Lambda_1^{(k)},\, \min(0,\,-U_1^{(k)}) \big\rangle + \big\langle \Lambda_2^{(k)},\, \min(0,\,-U_2^{(k)}) \big\rangle \Bigg], \end{aligned} \end{equation}\] <p>with matrix–matrix inner product</p> \[\begin{equation} \left\langle A, B \right\rangle = \sum_{j,\ell} A_{j\ell} B_{j\ell}. \end{equation}\] <p>In the method of multipliers, Lagrange multipliers are treated as dual variables that are updated each iteration:</p> \[\begin{equation} \Lambda_i^{(k+1)} = [\Lambda_i^{(k)} + \mu^{(k)}~\left(\min\left(0,\,-U_i^{(k)}\right) \right) ]_+, \end{equation}\] <p>where $[\cdot]_+ = \max(0,\cdot)$ clips negative entries to zero, ensuring that all Lagrange multipliers are positive (each element of $\Lambda_i^{(k)}$ is a Lagrange multiplier).</p> <h2 id="the-levenbergmarquardt-algorithm-for-leastsquares-problems">The Levenberg–Marquardt Algorithm for Least–Squares Problems</h2> <p>The Levenberg–Marquardt algorithm is a workhorse tool for solving both linear and nonlinear least–squares problems with objective function $\frac{1}{2} \left\lVert r \right\rVert_\text{F}^2$. This algorithm can be thought of as an extension of the Gauss–Newton algorithm that incorporates a trust region for regularization. Let’s derive this algorithm with calculus.</p> <p>First, consider the optimization problem of identifying the parameter, $\hat{\beta}$, which minimizes the least–squares error of fitting observed data, $y$, with a curve, $f(x, \beta)$:</p> \[\begin{equation} \hat{\beta} \in \arg\min \frac{1}{2} \left\lVert y - f(x,\beta) \right\rVert_\text{F}^2, \end{equation}\] <p>where the loss function, $\mathcal{L}$, for this problem is the norm being minimized above:</p> \[\begin{equation} \mathcal{L} = \frac{1}{2} \left\lVert y - f(x,\beta) \right\rVert_\text{F}^2. \end{equation}\] <p>Let’s begin by linearizing function $f$ about $\beta$:</p> \[\begin{equation} f(x,\beta+\delta\beta) \approx f(x,\beta) + J\delta\beta, \end{equation}\] <p>where $J=\frac{\partial f(x,\beta)}{\partial\beta}$ is the Jacobian of $f$.</p> <p>This linearized $f$ is then plugged into the original residual to define a new loss function in terms of observed data, $y$; fit curve, $f$; Jacobian, $J$; and optimization parameter step, $\delta\beta$:</p> \[\begin{equation} \begin{aligned} \mathcal{L} &amp;= \frac{1}{2} \left\lVert y - f(x,\beta) \right\rVert_\text{F}^2 \\ &amp;\approx \frac{1}{2} \left\lVert\, y - \left(f(x,\beta) + J\delta\beta\right) \right\rVert_\text{F}^2 \\ &amp;= \frac{1}{2}\,\big(y - f(x,\beta) - J\delta\beta\big)^\top \big(y - f(x,\beta) - J\delta\beta\big) \\ &amp;= \frac{1}{2}(y^\top - f^\top(x,\beta) - \delta\beta^\top J^\top)(y - f(x,\beta) - J\delta\beta) \\ &amp;= \frac{1}{2} \left( y^\top y + f^\top f - 2y^\top f - 2y^\top J \delta\beta + 2f^\top J \delta\beta + \delta\beta^\top J^\top J \delta\beta \right). \end{aligned} \end{equation}\] <p>We want to compute the optimization step $\delta\beta$ that yields the minimal loss relative to our current position in the loss landscape, so let’s compute the gradient of this loss function with respect to $\delta\beta$:</p> \[\begin{equation} \begin{aligned} \frac{\partial\mathcal{L}}{\partial(\delta\beta)} &amp;= \frac{1}{2}(0 + 0 - 0 - 2y^\top J + 2f^\top(x,\beta) J + 2J^\top J\delta\beta) \\ &amp;= -y^\top J + f^\top(x,\beta) J + J^\top J\delta\beta \\ &amp;= J^\top J\delta\beta - (y^\top - f^\top(x,\beta))J. \end{aligned} \end{equation}\] <p>Finally, setting this derivative equal to zero yields a system of linear equations used to compute the optimal step of optimization parameter $\beta$:</p> \[\begin{equation} \begin{aligned} 0 &amp;\overset{!}{=} J^\top J\delta\beta - (y^\top - f^\top(x,\beta))J \\ J^\top J\delta\beta &amp;= (y^\top - f^\top(x,\beta))J \\ J^\top J\delta\beta &amp;= J^\top(y - f(x,\beta)), \end{aligned} \end{equation}\] <p>where the $\overset{!}{=}$ form of the familiar $=$ symbol conveys that we are coercing the expression to equal $0$. Application of this equation is known as the Gauss–Newton algorithm.</p> <p>Solving the system of linear equations in the Gauss–Newton algorithm may, however, be ill–posed due to an ill–conditioned $J^\top J$. This conditioning can be improved through the following regularization:</p> \[\begin{equation} (J^\top J + \gamma I)\delta\beta = J^\top(y - f(x,\beta)), \end{equation}\] <p>yielding a system of linear equations whose application is known as the Levenberg–Marquardt algorithm.</p> <p>There are various benefits to adding $\gamma I$ to $J^\top J$, namely those stemming from increasing the positive–definiteness of the system matrix. To convey these benefits, let’s first use the Rayleigh–Ritz quotient to show that eigenvalues of $J^\top J + \gamma I$ are larger than those of $J^\top J$ when $\gamma &gt; 0$:</p> \[\begin{equation} \begin{aligned} (J^\top J + \gamma I)x_i &amp;= \lambda_i^{\text{LM}} x_i \\ x_i^\top (J^\top J + \gamma I)x_i &amp;= \lambda_i^{\text{LM}} x^\top_i x_i \\ \lambda_i^{\text{LM}} &amp;= \frac{x_i^\top (J^\top J + \gamma I)x_i}{x^\top_i x_i} \\ \lambda_i^{\text{LM}} &amp;= \frac{x_i^\top (J^\top J)x_i}{x^\top_i x_i} + \frac{x_i^\top (\gamma I) x_i}{x^\top_i x_i} \\ \lambda_i^{\text{LM}} &amp;= \lambda_i^{\text{GN}} + \gamma, \end{aligned} \end{equation}\] <p>where $\lambda_i^{\text{LM}}$ is the $i$th largest eigenvalue of $J^\top J + \gamma I$, $\lambda_i^{\text{GN}}$ is the $i$th largest eigenvalue of $J^\top J$, and $\gamma \geq 0$. Thus, adding a sufficiently large value of $\gamma$ will make the system matrix in the Levenberg–Marquardt algorithm symmetric positive–definite. Importantly, if $J^\top J + \gamma I$ is symmetric positive–definite (meaning that it’s symmetric and all eigenvalues are positive), then:</p> <ul> <li>there exists a unique solution for $\delta\beta$</li> <li>the step taken is always a descent direction</li> <li>conjugate gradient, a fast and numerically stable solver, can be used.</li> </ul> <p>Appropriately choosing $\gamma$ can significantly reduce the condition number of the system matrix at hand. As a simple example, let’s assume that $J^\top J$ is a symmetric positive–definite matrix such that its singular values are its eigenvalues, yielding a condition number $\kappa(J^\top J) = \lambda_1^{\text{GN}} / \lambda_n^{\text{GN}}$. Let’s assert that $\lambda_1^{\text{GN}}=100$ and $\lambda_n^{\text{GN}}=0.0001$ such that $\kappa(J^\top J) = 100 / 0.0001 = 1,000,000$—a very ill–conditioned system! Despite this enormous condition number, the condition number of $J^\top J + \gamma I$ with $\gamma=1$ is orders of magnitude smaller: $\kappa(J^\top J + 1I) = (\lambda_1^{\text{GN}} + 1) / (\lambda_n^{\text{GN}}+1) = (100 + 1) / (0.0001 + 1) = 100.99$. Notably, the Levenberg–Marquardt algorithm interpolates between Gauss–Newton and gradient descent: $\gamma=0$ yields Gauss–Newton; $\gamma\gg 0$ yields gradient descent.</p> <p>Finally, the solution can be made scale invariant by regularizing with a diagonal matrix formed directly from $J^TJ$ instead of with an arbitrarily chosen identity matrix:</p> \[\begin{equation} (J^\top J + \gamma\,\mathrm{diag}(J^\top J))\delta\beta = J^\top(y - f(x,\beta)). \end{equation}\] <p>A diagonal matrix (rather than one with arbitrarily located nonzero elements) is added for regularization to preserve symmetry.</p> <h2 id="jax-for-physicsinformed-source-separation">JAX for Physics–Informed Source Separation</h2> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posts/physics-informed-source-separation/U1_reconstruction-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/posts/physics-informed-source-separation/U1_reconstruction-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/posts/physics-informed-source-separation/U1_reconstruction-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/physics-informed-source-separation/U1_reconstruction.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posts/physics-informed-source-separation/U_sum_true-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/posts/physics-informed-source-separation/U_sum_true-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/posts/physics-informed-source-separation/U_sum_true-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/physics-informed-source-separation/U_sum_true.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posts/physics-informed-source-separation/U2_reconstruction-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/posts/physics-informed-source-separation/U2_reconstruction-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/posts/physics-informed-source-separation/U2_reconstruction-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/physics-informed-source-separation/U2_reconstruction.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Click on an image to enlarge it. <strong>Left:</strong> Inferred source one from physics--informed source separation. <strong>Middle:</strong> True source one + true source two. <strong>Right:</strong> Inferred source two from physics--informed source separation. </div> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posts/physics-informed-source-separation/U1_reconstruction-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/posts/physics-informed-source-separation/U1_reconstruction-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/posts/physics-informed-source-separation/U1_reconstruction-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/physics-informed-source-separation/U1_reconstruction.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posts/physics-informed-source-separation/U1_error-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/posts/physics-informed-source-separation/U1_error-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/posts/physics-informed-source-separation/U1_error-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/physics-informed-source-separation/U1_error.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Click on an image to enlarge it. <strong>Left:</strong> Inferred source one from physics--informed source separation. <strong>Right:</strong> Elementwise difference between true source one and inferred source one, with Frobenius norm percentage error. </div> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posts/physics-informed-source-separation/U2_reconstruction-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/posts/physics-informed-source-separation/U2_reconstruction-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/posts/physics-informed-source-separation/U2_reconstruction-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/physics-informed-source-separation/U2_reconstruction.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posts/physics-informed-source-separation/U2_error-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/posts/physics-informed-source-separation/U2_error-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/posts/physics-informed-source-separation/U2_error-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/physics-informed-source-separation/U2_error.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Click on an image to enlarge it. <strong>Left:</strong> Inferred source one from physics--informed source separation. <strong>Right:</strong> Elementwise difference between true source two and inferred source two, with Frobenius norm percentage error. </div> <p>JAX is an incredible Python library that facilitates the use of automatic differentiation to easily compute Jacobians for numerical optimization (and anywhere else they may be used, such as in the numerical solution of nonlinear systems of ordinary differential equations using Newton’s method). One can also use it for just–in–time (JIT) compilation but we do not do so here. This library forms the backbone of another called JAXopt, which has an intuitive interface for calling a routine that uses the Levenberg–Marquardt algorithm to solve a least–squares problem, such as the one we posed using physics–informed regularization. The following illustrates how to solve the optimization problem we’ve discussed so far through JAXopt.</p> <p>First, imports:</p> <div class="language-python highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="kn">import</span> <span class="n">numpy</span> <span class="k">as</span> <span class="n">np</span>
<span class="kn">import</span> <span class="n">matplotlib.pyplot</span> <span class="k">as</span> <span class="n">plt</span>
<span class="kn">import</span> <span class="n">jax</span>
<span class="kn">import</span> <span class="n">jax.numpy</span> <span class="k">as</span> <span class="n">jnp</span>
<span class="kn">import</span> <span class="n">jaxopt</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Next, define helper functions for finite–difference simulation of the superposition of advecting signals:</p> <div class="language-python highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="c1"># helper functions
</span><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">get_fwd_diff_op</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">u</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">dx</span><span class="p">):</span>
    <span class="n">n</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">u</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">shape</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">]</span>
    <span class="n">main_diag</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">1</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">np</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">ones</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">n</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="n">super_diag</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">np</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">ones</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">n</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="n">K</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">np</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">diag</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">main_diag</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="n">np</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">diag</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">super_diag</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">k</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="n">K</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">1</span>
    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="n">K</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">1</span> <span class="o">/</span> <span class="n">dx</span><span class="p">)</span>

<span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">get_bwd_diff_op</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">u</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">dx</span><span class="p">):</span>
    <span class="n">n</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">u</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">shape</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">]</span>
    <span class="n">main_diag</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">np</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">ones</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">n</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="n">sub_diag</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">1</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">np</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">ones</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">n</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="n">K</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">np</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">diag</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">main_diag</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="n">np</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">diag</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">sub_diag</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">k</span><span class="o">=-</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="n">K</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">1</span>
    <span class="n">K</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">1</span>
    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="n">K</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">1</span> <span class="o">/</span> <span class="n">dx</span><span class="p">)</span>

<span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">get_u_next</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">u_curr</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">a</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">dt</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">Kfwd</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">Kbwd</span><span class="p">):</span>
    <span class="n">D</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">Kbwd</span> <span class="k">if</span> <span class="n">a</span> <span class="o">&gt;=</span> <span class="mf">0.0</span> <span class="k">else</span> <span class="n">Kfwd</span>
    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="n">u_curr</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">a</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">dt</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">D</span> <span class="o">@</span> <span class="n">u_curr</span><span class="p">)</span>

<span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">get_u0</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">x</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">mu</span><span class="p">):</span>
    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="n">np</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">exp</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="p">((</span><span class="n">x</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="n">mu</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">**</span> <span class="mi">2</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">/</span> <span class="mf">0.0002</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">/</span> <span class="n">np</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">sqrt</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mf">0.0002</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">np</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">pi</span><span class="p">)</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Then, simulate the individual advection of two Gaussian pulses traveling towards and through each other:</p> <div class="language-python highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="c1"># space
</span><span class="n">x0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">xf</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mf">0.0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mf">1.0</span>
<span class="n">n</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">2</span><span class="o">**</span><span class="mi">7</span>
<span class="n">x</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">np</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">linspace</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">x0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">xf</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">num</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="n">n</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">endpoint</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="bp">False</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">dx</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">x</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="n">x</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">]</span>

<span class="c1"># speed
</span><span class="n">c1</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mf">10.0</span>
<span class="n">c2</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="o">-</span><span class="n">c1</span>

<span class="c1"># time
</span><span class="n">t0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">tf</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mf">0.0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mf">0.02</span>
<span class="n">courant_number</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mf">0.99</span>
<span class="n">dt</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">courant_number</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">dx</span> <span class="o">/</span> <span class="nf">max</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">abs</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">c1</span><span class="p">),</span> <span class="nf">abs</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">c2</span><span class="p">))</span>
<span class="n">N_steps</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nf">int</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">np</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">ceil</span><span class="p">((</span><span class="n">tf</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="n">t0</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">/</span> <span class="n">dt</span><span class="p">))</span>
<span class="n">dt</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">tf</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="n">t0</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">/</span> <span class="n">N_steps</span>
<span class="n">ts</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">np</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">linspace</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">t0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">tf</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">N_steps</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">endpoint</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="bp">True</span><span class="p">)</span>

<span class="c1"># snapshots
</span><span class="n">U1</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">np</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">zeros</span><span class="p">((</span><span class="n">n</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">N_steps</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">))</span>
<span class="n">U2</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">np</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">zeros</span><span class="p">((</span><span class="n">n</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">N_steps</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">))</span>

<span class="n">mu1</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mf">0.4</span>
<span class="n">mu2</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mf">1.0</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="n">mu1</span>
<span class="n">u1_curr</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nf">get_u0</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">x</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">mu1</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">u2_curr</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">2</span><span class="o">*</span><span class="nf">get_u0</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">x</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">mu2</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">U1</span><span class="p">[:,</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">u1_curr</span>
<span class="n">U2</span><span class="p">[:,</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">u2_curr</span>

<span class="c1"># FD operators
</span><span class="n">Kfwd</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nf">get_fwd_diff_op</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">u1_curr</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">dx</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">Kbwd</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nf">get_bwd_diff_op</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">u1_curr</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">dx</span><span class="p">)</span>

<span class="c1"># simulate
</span><span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">j</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="nf">range</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">N_steps</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">):</span>
    <span class="n">u1_curr</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nf">get_u_next</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">u1_curr</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">c1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">dt</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">Kfwd</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">Kbwd</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="n">U1</span><span class="p">[:,</span> <span class="n">j</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">u1_curr</span>

    <span class="n">u2_curr</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nf">get_u_next</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">u2_curr</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">c2</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">dt</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">Kfwd</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">Kbwd</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="n">U2</span><span class="p">[:,</span> <span class="n">j</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">u2_curr</span>

    <span class="k">if</span> <span class="n">j</span> <span class="o">%</span> <span class="mi">100</span> <span class="o">==</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">:</span>
        <span class="nf">print</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sa">f</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s"> Step </span><span class="si">{</span><span class="n">j</span><span class="si">:</span><span class="mi">4</span><span class="n">d</span><span class="si">}</span><span class="s">/</span><span class="si">{</span><span class="n">N_steps</span><span class="si">:</span><span class="mi">4</span><span class="n">d</span><span class="si">}</span><span class="s">, t = </span><span class="si">{</span><span class="n">ts</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">j</span><span class="p">]</span><span class="si">:</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="mi">5</span><span class="n">f</span><span class="si">}</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">)</span>

<span class="c1"># compute superposition solution
</span><span class="n">U</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">U1</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="n">U2</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Next, visualize the individual PDE solutions and their superposition (which will serve as our observed data that we wish to decompose via physics–informed source separation):</p> <div class="language-python highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="n">vmin</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">U</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">min</span><span class="p">()</span>
<span class="n">vmax</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">U</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">max</span><span class="p">()</span>

<span class="n">fig1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">ax1</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">plt</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">subplots</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">figsize</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">6</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">5</span><span class="p">))</span>
<span class="n">im0</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">ax1</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">imshow</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">U1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">extent</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">x0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">xf</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">tf</span><span class="p">),</span> <span class="n">aspect</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">auto</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">,</span>
                 <span class="n">vmin</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="n">vmin</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">vmax</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="n">vmax</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">ax1</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">set_xlabel</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sa">r</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">$t$</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">ax1</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">set_ylabel</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sa">r</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">$x$</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">ax1</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">set_title</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sa">r</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">$(U_1)_{\text{true}}$</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">plt</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">colorbar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">im0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">ax</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="n">ax1</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">fig1</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">tight_layout</span><span class="p">()</span>
<span class="n">fig1</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">savefig</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">U1_true.jpg</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">dpi</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">300</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">bbox_inches</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">tight</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">plt</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">close</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">fig1</span><span class="p">)</span>

<span class="n">fig2</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">ax2</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">plt</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">subplots</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">figsize</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">6</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">5</span><span class="p">))</span>
<span class="n">im1</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">ax2</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">imshow</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">U2</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">extent</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">x0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">xf</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">tf</span><span class="p">),</span> <span class="n">aspect</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">auto</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">,</span>
                 <span class="n">vmin</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="n">vmin</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">vmax</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="n">vmax</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">ax2</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">set_xlabel</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sa">r</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">$t$</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">ax2</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">set_ylabel</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sa">r</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">$x$</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">ax2</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">set_title</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sa">r</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">$(U_2)_{\text{true}}$</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">plt</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">colorbar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">im1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">ax</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="n">ax2</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">fig2</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">tight_layout</span><span class="p">()</span>
<span class="n">fig2</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">savefig</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">U2_true.jpg</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">dpi</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">300</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">bbox_inches</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">tight</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">plt</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">close</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">fig2</span><span class="p">)</span>

<span class="n">fig3</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">ax3</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">plt</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">subplots</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">figsize</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">6</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">5</span><span class="p">))</span>
<span class="n">im2</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">ax3</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">imshow</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">U</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">extent</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">x0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">xf</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">tf</span><span class="p">),</span> <span class="n">aspect</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">auto</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">,</span>
                 <span class="n">vmin</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="n">vmin</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">vmax</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="n">vmax</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">ax3</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">set_xlabel</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sa">r</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">$t$</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">ax3</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">set_ylabel</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sa">r</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">$x$</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">ax3</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">set_title</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sa">r</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">$(U_1)_{\text{true}} + (U_2)_{\text{true}}$</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">plt</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">colorbar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">im2</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">ax</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="n">ax3</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">fig3</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">tight_layout</span><span class="p">()</span>
<span class="n">fig3</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">savefig</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">U_sum_true.jpg</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">dpi</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">300</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">bbox_inches</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">tight</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">plt</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">close</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">fig3</span><span class="p">)</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>After that, define helper functions for computing the residual that will be minimized:</p> <div class="language-python highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">dUdt_center</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">U</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">dt</span><span class="p">):</span>
    <span class="nf">return </span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">U</span><span class="p">[:,</span> <span class="mi">2</span><span class="p">:]</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="n">U</span><span class="p">[:,</span> <span class="p">:</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">2</span><span class="p">])</span> <span class="o">/</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">2</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">dt</span><span class="p">)</span>

<span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">dUdx_center</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">U</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">dx</span><span class="p">):</span>
    <span class="nf">return </span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">U</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">2</span><span class="p">:,</span> <span class="p">:]</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="n">U</span><span class="p">[:</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">2</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="p">:])</span> <span class="o">/</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">2</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">dx</span><span class="p">)</span>

<span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">pde_res</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">U</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">c</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">dt</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">dx</span><span class="p">):</span>
    <span class="n">dt_term</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nf">dUdt_center</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">U</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">dt</span><span class="p">)[</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="p">:]</span>
    <span class="n">dx_term</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nf">dUdx_center</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">U</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">dx</span><span class="p">)[:,</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">]</span>
    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="n">dt_term</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="n">c</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">dx_term</span>

<span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">get_residual</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">U_obs</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">dx</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">dt</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">c1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">c2</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">reg_pde1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">reg_pde2</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">mu</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">lam_1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">lam_2</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">x</span><span class="p">):</span>
    <span class="n">nx</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">nt</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">U_obs</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">shape</span>
    <span class="n">U12</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">x</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">reshape</span><span class="p">((</span><span class="mi">2</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">nx</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">nt</span><span class="p">))</span>
    <span class="n">U1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">U2</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">U12</span><span class="p">[:</span><span class="n">nx</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="p">:],</span> <span class="n">U12</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">nx</span><span class="p">:,</span> <span class="p">:]</span>

    <span class="n">r_dec</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">U1</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="n">U2</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="n">U_obs</span>
    <span class="n">r_pde1</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">jnp</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">sqrt</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mf">2.0</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">reg_pde1</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="nf">pde_res</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">U1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">c1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">dt</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">dx</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="n">r_pde2</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">jnp</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">sqrt</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mf">2.0</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">reg_pde2</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="nf">pde_res</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">U2</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">c2</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">dt</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">dx</span><span class="p">)</span>

    <span class="n">viol1</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="o">-</span><span class="n">jnp</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">minimum</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">U1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mf">0.0</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="n">viol2</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="o">-</span><span class="n">jnp</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">minimum</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">U2</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mf">0.0</span><span class="p">)</span>

    <span class="n">r_pen1</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">jnp</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">sqrt</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">mu</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">viol1</span>
    <span class="n">r_pen2</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">jnp</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">sqrt</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">mu</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">viol2</span>

    <span class="n">r_mm1</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">jnp</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">sum</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">lam_1</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">viol1</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="n">r_mm2</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">jnp</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">sum</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">lam_2</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">viol2</span><span class="p">)</span>

    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="n">jnp</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">concatenate</span><span class="p">([</span>
        <span class="n">r_dec</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">ravel</span><span class="p">(),</span>
        <span class="n">r_pde1</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">ravel</span><span class="p">(),</span>
        <span class="n">r_pde2</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">ravel</span><span class="p">(),</span>
        <span class="n">r_pen1</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">ravel</span><span class="p">(),</span>
        <span class="n">r_pen2</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">ravel</span><span class="p">(),</span>
        <span class="n">jnp</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">atleast_1d</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">r_mm1</span><span class="p">),</span>
        <span class="n">jnp</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">atleast_1d</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">r_mm2</span><span class="p">),</span>
    <span class="p">])</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Now pose the physics–informed source separation problem with JAX’s <em>jax.numpy</em> syntax. With residuals defined in this way, the Levenberg–Marquardt algorithm can be implemented to compute optimal $U_1$ and $U_2$ through the <em>jaxopt.LevenbergMarquardt</em> method:</p> <div class="language-python highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="n">nx</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">nt</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">U</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">shape</span>
<span class="n">x</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">jnp</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">concatenate</span><span class="p">([</span><span class="n">U</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">U</span><span class="p">],</span> <span class="n">axis</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">).</span><span class="nf">ravel</span><span class="p">()</span>

<span class="n">lam_pde1</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mf">1e-6</span>
<span class="n">lam_pde2</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mf">1e-6</span>

<span class="n">mu</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mf">1e3</span>
<span class="n">mu_max</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mf">1e6</span>
<span class="n">outer_iters</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">2</span>
<span class="n">lm_maxiter</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">50</span>

<span class="n">lam_1</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">jnp</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">zeros_like</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">U</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">lam_2</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">jnp</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">zeros_like</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">U</span><span class="p">)</span>

<span class="n">U1ks</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">U2ks</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">[],</span> <span class="p">[]</span>
<span class="n">U1_iters</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">U2_iters</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">[],</span> <span class="p">[]</span>

<span class="n">prev_viol</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">jnp</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">inf</span>

<span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">k</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="nf">range</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">outer_iters</span><span class="p">):</span>
    <span class="nf">print</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">outer iter</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">k</span><span class="p">)</span>

    <span class="n">solver</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">jaxopt</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nc">LevenbergMarquardt</span><span class="p">(</span>
        <span class="n">residual_fun</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="k">lambda</span> <span class="n">x_</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="nf">get_residual</span><span class="p">(</span>
            <span class="n">U</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">dx</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">dt</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">c1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">c2</span><span class="p">,</span>
            <span class="n">lam_pde1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">lam_pde2</span><span class="p">,</span>
            <span class="n">mu</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">lam_1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">lam_2</span><span class="p">,</span>
            <span class="n">x_</span>
        <span class="p">),</span>
        <span class="n">maxiter</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="n">lm_maxiter</span>
    <span class="p">)</span>

    <span class="n">x</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">solver</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">run</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">init_params</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="n">x</span><span class="p">).</span><span class="n">params</span>

    <span class="n">U12</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">x</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">reshape</span><span class="p">((</span><span class="mi">2</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">nx</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">nt</span><span class="p">))</span>
    <span class="n">U1_k</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">U2_k</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">U12</span><span class="p">[:</span><span class="n">nx</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="p">:],</span> <span class="n">U12</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">nx</span><span class="p">:,</span> <span class="p">:]</span>
    <span class="n">U1ks</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">append</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">U1_k</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="n">U2ks</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">append</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">U2_k</span><span class="p">)</span>

    <span class="n">viol1</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="o">-</span><span class="n">jnp</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">minimum</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">U1_k</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mf">0.0</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="n">viol2</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="o">-</span><span class="n">jnp</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">minimum</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">U2_k</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mf">0.0</span><span class="p">)</span>

    <span class="n">lam_1</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">jnp</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">maximum</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mf">0.0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">lam_1</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="n">mu</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">viol1</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="n">lam_2</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">jnp</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">maximum</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mf">0.0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">lam_2</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="n">mu</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">viol2</span><span class="p">)</span>

    <span class="n">viol</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">jnp</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">sqrt</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">jnp</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">linalg</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">norm</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">viol1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">fro</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="o">**</span><span class="mi">2</span> <span class="o">+</span>
                    <span class="n">jnp</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">linalg</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">norm</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">viol2</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">fro</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="o">**</span><span class="mi">2</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="k">if</span> <span class="nf">float</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">viol</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">&lt;</span> <span class="mf">0.8</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="nf">float</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">prev_viol</span><span class="p">):</span>
        <span class="n">mu</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nf">min</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">mu_max</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mf">2.0</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">mu</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="n">prev_viol</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">viol</span>

<span class="n">U_hat</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">np</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">array</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">x</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">reshape</span><span class="p">((</span><span class="mi">2</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">nx</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">nt</span><span class="p">)))</span>
<span class="n">U1_hat</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">U2_hat</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">U_hat</span><span class="p">[:</span><span class="n">nx</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="p">:],</span> <span class="n">U_hat</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">nx</span><span class="p">:,</span> <span class="p">:]</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Last but not least, visualize the sources inferred through our solved physics–informed source separation problem:</p> <div class="language-python highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="n">rel_err</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">np</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">linalg</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">norm</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">U1</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="n">U1ks</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">],</span> <span class="nb">ord</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">fro</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">/</span> <span class="n">np</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">linalg</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">norm</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">U1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nb">ord</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">fro</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">perc_err</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">100</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">rel_err</span>

<span class="n">fig_recon</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">ax_recon</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">plt</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">subplots</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">figsize</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">6</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">5</span><span class="p">))</span>
<span class="n">im0</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">ax_recon</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">imshow</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">U1ks</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">],</span> <span class="n">extent</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">x0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">xf</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">tf</span><span class="p">),</span> <span class="n">aspect</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">auto</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">vmin</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="n">vmin</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">vmax</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="n">vmax</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">ax_recon</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">set_xlabel</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sa">r</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">$t$</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">ax_recon</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">set_ylabel</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sa">r</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">$x$</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">ax_recon</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">set_title</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sa">r</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">$\hat{U}_1$</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">plt</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">colorbar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">im0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">ax</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="n">ax_recon</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">fig_recon</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">tight_layout</span><span class="p">()</span>
<span class="n">fig_recon</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">savefig</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">U1_reconstruction.jpg</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">dpi</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">300</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">bbox_inches</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">tight</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">plt</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">close</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">fig_recon</span><span class="p">)</span>

<span class="n">fig_err</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">ax_err</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">plt</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">subplots</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">figsize</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">6</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">5</span><span class="p">))</span>
<span class="n">err</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">U1</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="n">U1ks</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">]</span>
<span class="n">im1</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">ax_err</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">imshow</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">err</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">extent</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">x0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">xf</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">tf</span><span class="p">),</span> <span class="n">aspect</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">auto</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">ax_err</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">set_xlabel</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sa">r</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">$t$</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">ax_err</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">set_ylabel</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sa">r</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">$x$</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">ax_err</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">set_title</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sa">r</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">$(U_1)_{\text{true}} - \hat{U}_1$, </span><span class="sh">'</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="sa">rf</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">Relative Error = </span><span class="si">{</span><span class="n">perc_err</span><span class="si">:</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="mi">2</span><span class="n">f</span><span class="si">}</span><span class="s">%</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">plt</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">colorbar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">im1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">ax</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="n">ax_err</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">fig_err</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">tight_layout</span><span class="p">()</span>
<span class="n">fig_err</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">savefig</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">U1_error.jpg</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">dpi</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">300</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">bbox_inches</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">tight</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">plt</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">close</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">fig_err</span><span class="p">)</span>

<span class="n">rel_err</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">np</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">linalg</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">norm</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">U2</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="n">U2ks</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">],</span> <span class="nb">ord</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">fro</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">/</span> <span class="n">np</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">linalg</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">norm</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">U2</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nb">ord</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">fro</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">perc_err</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">100</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">rel_err</span>

<span class="n">fig_recon</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">ax_recon</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">plt</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">subplots</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">figsize</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">6</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">5</span><span class="p">))</span>
<span class="n">im0</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">ax_recon</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">imshow</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">U2ks</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">],</span> <span class="n">extent</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">x0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">xf</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">tf</span><span class="p">),</span> <span class="n">aspect</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">auto</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">vmin</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="n">vmin</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">vmax</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="n">vmax</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">ax_recon</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">set_xlabel</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sa">r</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">$t$</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">ax_recon</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">set_ylabel</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sa">r</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">$x$</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">ax_recon</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">set_title</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sa">r</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">$\hat{U}_2$</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">plt</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">colorbar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">im0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">ax</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="n">ax_recon</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">fig_recon</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">tight_layout</span><span class="p">()</span>
<span class="n">fig_recon</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">savefig</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">U2_reconstruction.jpg</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">dpi</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">300</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">bbox_inches</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">tight</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">plt</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">close</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">fig_recon</span><span class="p">)</span>

<span class="n">fig_err</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">ax_err</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">plt</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">subplots</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">figsize</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">6</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">5</span><span class="p">))</span>
<span class="n">err</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">U2</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="n">U2ks</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">]</span>
<span class="n">im1</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">ax_err</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">imshow</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">err</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">extent</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">x0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">xf</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">tf</span><span class="p">),</span> <span class="n">aspect</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">auto</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">ax_err</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">set_xlabel</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sa">r</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">$t$</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">ax_err</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">set_ylabel</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sa">r</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">$x$</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">ax_err</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">set_title</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sa">r</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">$(U_2)_{\text{true}} - \hat{U}_2$, </span><span class="sh">'</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="sa">rf</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">Relative Error = </span><span class="si">{</span><span class="n">perc_err</span><span class="si">:</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="mi">2</span><span class="n">f</span><span class="si">}</span><span class="s">%</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">plt</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">colorbar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">im1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">ax</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="n">ax_err</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">fig_err</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">tight_layout</span><span class="p">()</span>
<span class="n">fig_err</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">savefig</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">U2_error.jpg</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">dpi</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">300</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">bbox_inches</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">tight</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">plt</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">close</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">fig_err</span><span class="p">)</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2> <p>In this post we demonstrated how to use JAX and JAXopt to implement the Levenberg–Marquardt algorithm for solving a least–squares problem whose objective function is formulated using the method of multipliers (aka, augmented Lagrangian method). This was applied to physics–informed source separation of the superposition of two advecting signals, with physics prescribed by 1D linear advection.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="numerical-methods"/><category term="ML"/><category term="optimization"/><category term="PDEs"/><category term="inverse-problems"/><category term="physics--informed"/><category term="JAX"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Formulation and numerical solution of a PDE source separation inverse problem that is regularized with physics--informed a priori information.]]></summary></entry></feed>