<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://jburz2001.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://jburz2001.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-11-14T21:59:24+00:00</updated><id>https://jburz2001.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Justin Burzachiello&apos;s personal website. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">JAX for Physics–Informed Source Separation</title><link href="https://jburz2001.github.io/blog/2025/jax-for-physics-informed-source-separation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="JAX for Physics–Informed Source Separation"/><published>2025-11-13T14:14:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-11-13T14:14:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jburz2001.github.io/blog/2025/jax-for-physics-informed-source-separation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jburz2001.github.io/blog/2025/jax-for-physics-informed-source-separation/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="source-separation-from-smoothies-to-pdes">Source Separation: From Smoothies to PDEs</h2> <p>Physical systems are often measured as mixtures of signals. For instance, seismometers measure not only the magnitude of earthquakes but also any other vibrations significant enough to register, such as mining explosions. Such extraneous signals can corrupt measurements (e.g., pressure waves from mining explosions mixed with seismic pressure waves from earthquakes), so it is often vital to isolate the signals of interest. This process is called <em>source separation</em> and is a type of inverse problem since the goal is to infer the original source signals (i.e., causes) from a collection of observed mixtures (i.e., effects). Source separation problems are often blind due to the absence of a well–defined model for how the constituent signals were mixed or of the sources themselves.</p> <p>As an analogy for blind source separation, imagine if I concocted a delicious smoothie and tasked you with reverse engineering the recipe! With training, you can become better at deconstructing the smoothie by incorporating knowledge of how smoothies are typically made, how Justin likes to make smoothies, which ingredients are reasonable for smoothies, etc. This accumulated knowledge of “smoothie deconstruction” can be thought of in a statistical sense as <em>a priori</em> information. One could take this analogy further by assuming that this <em>a priori</em> information represents a Bayesian prior that updates over time with each taste test! Training a machine learning model with this <em>a priori</em> information would be an instance of smoothie–informed machine learning.</p> <p>Fortunately, unlike smoothies, many physical systems yield observed signals whose constituent mixed sources abide by known partial differential equations (PDEs), such as the linear advection equation.<d-footnote Please="" contact="" me="" if="" you="" know="" of="" a="" PDE="" for="" smoothies.=""> This information can be leveraged as *a priori* information, yielding physics--informed source separation algorithms with improved efficiency, accuracy, and mathematical well--posedness.</d-footnote></p> <p>This post elaborates on these points by explaining:</p> <ul> <li>An example blind source separation (BSS) problem from physics</li> <li>How to regularize the aforementioned BSS problem with physically meaningful loss terms that incorporate <em>a priori</em> information about the constituent source signals</li> <li>The penalty method for converting numerical constrained optimization problems into unconstrained ones</li> <li>The Gauss–Newton algorithm and Levenberg–Marquardt algorithm for solving nonlinear least–squares problems</li> <li>Implementation in Python using Numpy, JAX, and JAXopt libraries for high–performance computing–based numerical simulation of PDEs and optimization.</li> </ul> <h2 id="linear-advection-pde">Linear Advection PDE</h2> <p>Physics is often expressed in the language of partial differential equations (PDEs). These equations leverage partial derivatives to model how multivariate dependent variables respond to changes in their independent variables, often space and time. For instance, the linear advection equation models how the value of an advected quantity changes according to the spatial gradient of that quantity and the underlying velocity field. The algebraic structure of this PDE and the spectral properties of the differential operators composing it conspire together to model translational motion called advection.</p> <p>This post demonstrates JAX for physics–informed source separation with simulated data from a 1–dimensional linear advection PDE. This equation is linear, ubiquitous, and well–suited to modeling the transport of localized signals that are easily distinguished by the naked eye but not necessarily to a <em>blind</em> source separation algorithm. Linearity of the advection equation is particularly helpful here since it allows us to easily model the (trivially) coupled evolution of multiple advecting signals by virtue of the principle of superposition:</p> \[\frac{\partial(\sum_{i=1}^{n}u_i)}{\partial t} + \frac{\partial (\sum_{i=1}^{n}c_i u_i)}{\partial x} = 0 = \sum_{i=1}^{n}(\frac{\partial u_i}{\partial t} + \frac{\partial (c_i u_i)}{\partial x}),\] <p>where $u = \sum_{i=1}^{n}u_i$ is the observed signal and $f = \sum_{i=1}^{n}c_i u_i$ is the total flux.</p> <p>The rest of this post will assume that there are only two advecting pulses, yielding the following model of the observed flow field:</p> \[\sum_{i=1}^{2}(\frac{\partial u_i}{\partial t} + \frac{\partial (c_i u_i)}{\partial x})=0,\] <p>where $c_i$ are constants quantifying advection speed. In general, determining the optimal value of $n$ (i.e., the number of sources being mixed) may not be trivial. However, there are plenty of data–driven methods to accomplish this. For instance, one could apply the line Hough transform to the Mikowski spacetime diagram of the observed solution then compute the number of disjoint maxima in this Hough space.</p> <h2 id="constrained-optimization-for-physics--informed-source-separation">Constrained Optimization for Physics–Informed Source Separation</h2> <p>Recall that our observed signal is the superposition of multiple individually advecting signals. As such, we can pose the following BSS problem:</p> \[(U_1, U_2) \in \arg\min_{U_1,U_2}\frac{1}{2}|| U_1 + U_2 - U ||_\text{F}^2,\] <p>where $U_1\in\mathbb{R}^{n\times K}$ is a matrix whose $j$th column is source one at timestamp $j$, $u_1(:, t_j)$; $U_2\in\mathbb{R}^{n\times K}$ is a matrix whose $j$th column is source two at timestamp $j$, $u_2(:, t_j)$; and $U\in\mathbb{R}^{n\times K}$ is a matrix whose $j$th column is observed signal at timestamps $j$, $u(:, t_j)$. The $1/2$ in front of the Frobenius norm is a <em>fudge factor</em> used to remove irrelevant coefficients of $2$ from gradients of the norm respect to design variables $U_1$, $U_2$, or $W=[U_1^\top \quad U_2^\top]^\top$ where $U_1 + U_2 - U = [I \quad I]~W - U$. Neglecting this $1/2$ does not change the optimal $(U_1,U_2)$.</p> <p>This BSS problem is unfortunately ill–posed since there are many equivalently–optimal solutions, most of which are physically meaningless. For instance, both $(U_1,U_2)=(U,0)$ and $(U_1,U_2)=(0,U)$ are valid solutions even though we assume $U_1\neq0\neq U_2$ by formulation of the residual in the norm being minimized. This ill–posedness is a common obstacle in the solution of computational inverse problems, such as source separation. Fortunately, <em>a priori</em> knowledge of signals $U_1$ and $U_2$ can be leveraged to regularize this problem, making it well–posed. One such regularization enforces that $U_1$ and $U_2$ are non–negative matrices:</p> \[(U_1, U_2) \in \arg\min_{U_1\geq 0,U_2\geq 0}\frac{1}{2}|| U_1 + U_2 - U ||_\text{F}^2.\] <p>Additionally, we can assume that $U_1$ and $U_2$ satisfy their own advection equations:</p> \[(U_1, U_2) \in \arg\min_{U_1\geq 0,U_2\geq 0}\frac{1}{2}|| U_1 + U_2 - U ||_\text{F}^2 + \lambda_{\text{PDE}_1} || \dot{U}_1 + c_1 U^\prime_1 ||_\text{F}^2 + \lambda_{\text{PDE}_2} || \dot{U}_2 + c_2 U^\prime_2 ||_\text{F}^2,\] <p>where $\dot{U}_i$ is a finite–difference–computed time derivative of $U_i$ and $U^\prime_i$ is a finite–difference–computed spatial derivative. Constants $c_i$ can be computed from observed snapshots $U$, such as by setting $c_i = 1/\text{slope}_i$, where $\text{slope}_i$ is the slope of the $i$th line detected in Hough space via the line Hough transform of $U$.</p> <h2 id="unconstrained-optimization-for-physics--informed-source-separation">Unconstrained Optimization for Physics–Informed Source Separation</h2> <p>Our constrained optimization problem can be converted into an unconstrained one through the penalty method. Doing so enables the solution of our constrained optimization problem by using optimizers for unconstrained problems:</p> \[(U_1^{(k)}, U_2^{(k)}) \in \arg\min_{U_1^{(k)},U_2^{(k)}}\frac{1}{2}|| U_1^{(k)} + U_2^{(k)} - U ||_\text{F}^2 + \lambda_{\text{PDE}_1} || \dot{U}^{(k)}_1 + c_1 U^{(k)\prime}_1 ||_\text{F}^2 + \lambda_{\text{PDE}_2} || \dot{U}^{(k)}_2 + c_2 U^{(k)\prime}_2 ||_\text{F}^2 + \frac{1}{2}\mu^{(k)}(|| \min(0, U_1^{(k)}) ||_\text{F}^2 + || \min(0, U_2^{(k)}) ||_\text{F}^2),\] <p>where $\min$ is a function that computes the elementwise minimum of a matrix with the zero matrix of the same shape, thus penalizing negative values. Index $k$ is used to convey the $k$th iteration of the penalty method. In practice, one often starts the optimization procedure using a small value of $\mu^{(k)}$; obtains $(U_1^{(k)}, U_2^{(k)})$; then recursively solves for $(U_1^{(k+1)}, U_2^{(k+1)})$ until convergence using $\mu^{(k+1)} &gt; \mu^{(k)}$, where $(U_1^{(k)}, U_2^{(k)})$ is the initial guess of $(U_1^{(k+1)}, U_2^{(k+1)})$.</p> <p>Furthermore, we can express this least–squares problem’s objective function to be minimized using a single norm:</p> \[(U_1^{(k)}, U_2^{(k)}) \in \arg\min_{U_1^{(k)}, U_2^{(k)}} \frac{1}{2} || \begin{bmatrix} U_1^{(k)} + U_2^{(k)} - U \\ 2\sqrt{\lambda_\text{PDE}}_1\,(\dot{U}^{(k)}_1 + c_1 U^{(k)\prime}_1) \\ 2\sqrt{\lambda_\text{PDE}}_1\,(\dot{U}^{(k)}_2 + c_2 U^{(k)\prime}_2) \\ \sqrt{\mu^{(k)}}\min(0, U_1^{(k)}) \\ \sqrt{\mu^{(k)}}\min(0, U_2^{(k)}) \end{bmatrix} ||_F^2 = \arg\min_{U_1^{(k)}, U_2^{(k)}} \frac{1}{2}|| r^{(k)} ||_\text{F}^2,\] <p>where $r^{(k)}$ is a single residual formed by stacking all constituent residuals in our objective function into a column vector. This notation with $r^{(k)}$ will facilitate the later use of the Levenberg–Marquardt algorithm for numerical optimization.</p> <h2 id="augmenting-the-penalty-method-with-lagrange-multipliers">Augmenting the Penalty Method With Lagrange Multipliers</h2> <p>Recall that we previously converted a constrained optimization problem into an unconstrained one using the penalty method. Intuitively, one recovers the constrained optimization solution in the limit as the penalty term, $\mu^{(k)}$, introduced by the penalty method, goes to infinity. Unfortunately, naively increasing $\mu^{(k)}$ towards infinity can make this optimization problem ill–posed if $\mu^{(k)}$ gets too large. However, one can circumvent the need to increase $\mu^{(k)}$ towards infinity by leveraging the method of multipliers (aka, the augmented Lagrangian method). The method of multipliers is analogous to the method of Lagrange multipliers from analytical optimization theory and forms the foundation of a standard tool in numerical optimization called the <em>alternating direction method of multipliers</em>, which is not covered in this post.</p> <p>Consider the following residual constructed by concatenating two additional loss terms to the $k$th iteration of the residual vector from before:</p> \[(U_1^{(k)}, U_2^{(k)}) \in \arg\min_{U_1^{(k)}, U_2^{(k)}} \frac{1}{2} || \begin{bmatrix} U_1^{(k)} + U_2^{(k)} - U \\ 2\sqrt{\lambda_\text{PDE}}_1\,(\dot{U}^{(k)}_1 + c_1 U^{(k)\prime}_1) \\ 2\sqrt{\lambda_\text{PDE}}_1\,(\dot{U}^{(k)}_2 + c_2 U^{(k)\prime}_2) \\ \sqrt{\mu^{(k)}}\min(0, U_1^{(k)}) \\ \sqrt{\mu^{(k)}}\min(0, U_2^{(k)}) \\ \frac{1}{2} \langle \Lambda_1^{(k)},\, U_1^{(k)} \rangle \\ \frac{1}{2} \langle \Lambda_2^{(k)},\, U_2^{(k)} \rangle \end{bmatrix} ||_F^2 = \arg\min_{U_1^{(k)}, U_2^{(k)}} \frac{1}{2}|| r^{(k)} ||_\text{F}^2,\] <p>with matrix–matrix inner product $\langle \Lambda_i^{(k)},\, U_i^{(k)}\rangle = \sum_{j,\ell} (\Lambda_i^{(k)})<em>{j\ell} (U_i^{(k)})</em>{j\ell}$.</p> <p>In the method of multipliers, Lagrange multipliers are treated as dual variables that are updated each iteration:</p> \[\Lambda_i^{(k+1)} = [\Lambda_i^{(k)} - \mu^{(k)}\,{U_i^{(k)}} ]_+,\] <p>where $[\cdot]_+ = \max(0,\cdot)$ clips negative entries to zero, ensuring that all Lagrange multipliers are positive (each element of $\Lambda_i^{(k)}$ is a Lagrange multiplier).</p> <h2 id="levenberg--marquardt-algorithm-for-nonlinear-least--squares-problems">Levenberg–Marquardt Algorithm for Nonlinear Least–Squares Problems</h2> <p>The Levenberg–Marquardt algorithm is a workhorse tool for solving both linear and nonlinear least–squares problems with objective function $\frac{1}{2}|| r ||_\text{F}^2$. This algorithm can be thought of as an extension of the Gauss–Newton algorithm that incorporates a trust region for regularization. Let’s derive this algorithm with calculus.</p> <p>First, consider the optimization problem of identifying the parameter, $\hat{\beta}$, which minimizes the least–squares error of fitting observed data, $y$, with a curve, $f(x, \beta)$:</p> \[\hat{\beta} \in \arg\min \frac{1}{2}|| y - f(x,\beta) ||_\text{F}^2,\] <p>where the loss function, $\mathcal{L}$, for this problem is the norm being minimized above:</p> \[\mathcal{L} = \frac{1}{2}|| y - f(x,\beta) ||_\text{F}^2.\] <p>Let’s begin by linearizing function $f$ about $\beta$:</p> \[f(x,\beta+\delta\beta) \approx f(x,\beta) + J\delta\beta,\] <p>where $J=\frac{\partial f(x,\beta)}{\partial\beta}$ is the Jacobian of $f$.</p> <p>This linearized $f$ is then plugged into the original residual to define a new loss function in terms of observed data, $y$; fit curve, $f$; Jacobian, $J$; and optimization parameter step; $\delta\beta$:</p> <p>\(\begin{align} \mathcal{L} &amp;= \frac{1}{2}|| y - f(x,\beta) ||_\text{F}^2 \\ \approx \frac{1}{2}||\, y - \left(f(x,\beta) + J\delta\beta\right) ||_\text{F}^2 \\ &amp;= \frac{1}{2}\,\big(y - f(x,\beta) - J\delta\beta\big)^\top \big(y - f(x,\beta) - J\delta\beta\big) \\ &amp;= \frac{1}{2}(y^\top - f^\top(x,\beta) - \delta\beta^\top J^\top)(y - f(x,\beta) - J\delta\beta) \\ &amp;= \frac{1}{2} \left(y^\top y - y^\top f(x,\beta) - y^\top J\delta\beta - f^\top(x,\beta)y + f^\top(x,\beta)f(x,\beta) + f^\top(x,\beta)J\delta\beta - \delta\beta^\top J^\top y + \delta\beta^\top J^\top f(x,\beta) + \delta\beta^\top J^\top J \delta\beta\right) \\ &amp;= \frac{1}{2} \left( y^\top y + f^\top f - 2y^\top f - 2y^\top J \delta\beta + 2f^\top J \delta\beta + \delta\beta^\top J^\top J \delta\beta \right) \end{align}\).</p> <p>We want to compute the optimization step $\delta\beta$ that yields the minimal loss relative to our current position in the loss landscape, so let’s compute the gradient of this loss function with respect to $\delta\beta$:</p> <p>\(\begin{align} \frac{\partial\mathcal{L}}{\partial(\delta\beta)} &amp;= \frac{1}{2}(0 + 0 - 0 - 2y^\top J + 2f^\top(x,\beta) J + 2J^\top J\delta\beta) \\ &amp;= -y^\top J + f^\top(x,\beta) J + J^\top J\delta\beta \\ &amp;= J^\top J\delta\beta - (y^\top - f^\top(x,\beta))J \end{align}\).</p> <p>Finally, setting this derivative equal to zero yields a system of linear equations used to compute the optimal step of optimization parameter $\beta$:</p> <p>\(\begin{align} J^\top J\delta\beta - (y^\top - f^\top(x,\beta))J &amp;\overset{!}{=} 0 \\ J^\top J\delta\beta &amp;= (y^\top - f^\top(x,\beta))J \\ J^\top J\delta\beta &amp;= J^\top(y - f(x,\beta)) \end{align}\),</p> <p>where the $\overset{!}{=}$ form of the familiar $=$ symbol conveys that we are coercing the expression to equal $0$. Application of this equation is known as the Gauss–Newton algorithm.</p> <p>Solving the system of linear equations in the Gauss–Newton algorithm may, however, be ill–posed due to an ill–conditioned $J^\top J$. This conditioning can be improved through the following regularization:</p> <p>\((J^\top J + \gamma I)\delta\beta = J^\top(y - f(x,\beta))\),</p> <p>yielding a system of linear equations whose application is known as the Levenberg–Marquardt algorithm.</p> <p>There are various benefits to adding $\gamma I$ to $J^\top J$, namely those stemming from increasing the positive–definiteness of the system matrix. To convey these benefits, let’s first use the Rayleigh–Ritz quotient to show that eigenvalues of $J^\top J + \gamma I$ are larger than those of $J^\top J$ when $\gamma \geq 0$:</p> \[\begin{align} (J^\top J + \gamma I)x_i &amp;= \lambda_i^{\text{LM}} x_i \\ x_i^\top (J^\top J + \gamma I)x_i &amp;= \lambda_i^{\text{LM}} x^\top_i x_i \\ \lambda_i^{\text{LM}} &amp;= \frac{x_i^\top (J^\top J + \gamma I)x_i}{x^\top_i x_i} \\ \lambda_i^{\text{LM}} &amp;= \frac{x_i^\top (J^\top J)x_i}{x^\top_i x_i} + \frac{x_i^\top (\gamma I) x_i}{x^\top_i x_i} \\ \lambda_i^{\text{LM}} &amp;= \lambda_i^{\text{GN}} + \gamma, \end{align}\] <p>where $\lambda_i^{\text{LM}}$ is the $i$th largest eigenvalue of $J^\top J + \gamma I$, $\lambda_i^{\text{GN}}$ is the $i$th largest eigenvalue of $J^\top J$, and $\gamma \geq 0$. Thus, adding a sufficiently large value of $\mu$ will make the system matrix in the Levenberg–Marquardt algorithm symmetric positive–definite. Importantly, if $J^\top J + \gamma I$ is symmetric positive–definite (meaning that it’s symmetric and all eigenvalues are positive), then:</p> <ul> <li>there exists a unique solution for $\delta\beta$</li> <li>the step taken is always a descent direction</li> <li>singular values of $J^\top J + \gamma I$ equal the eigenvalues and increase in magnitude with $\gamma$, increasing the condition number of the system matrix</li> <li>fast, numerically stable solvers can be used, like conjugate gradient.</li> </ul> <p>Appropriately choosing $\gamma$ can significantly reduce the condition number of the system matrix at hand. As a simple example, assume that $J^\top J$ a symmetric positive–definite matrix such that its singular values are its eigenvalues, yielding a condition number $\kappa(J^\top J) = \lambda_1^{\text{GN}} / \lambda_n^{\text{GN}}$. Let’s assert that $\lambda_1^{\text{GN}}=100$ and $\lambda_n^{\text{GN}}=0.0001$ such that $\kappa(J^\top J) = 100 / 0.0001 = 1,000,000$—a very ill–conditioned system! Despite this enormous condition number, the condition number of $J^\top J + \gamma I$ with $\mu=1$ is orders of magnitude smaller: $\kappa(J^\top J + 1I) = (\lambda_1^{\text{GN}} + 1) / (\lambda_n^{\text{GN}}+1) = (100 + 1) / (0.0001 + 1) = 101 / 1.0001 = 100.19$. Notably, the Levenberg–Marquardt algorithm interpolates between Gauss–Newton and gradient descent: $\mu=0$ yields Gauss–Newton; $\mu\gg 0$ yields gradient descent.</p> <p>Finally, the solution can be made scale invariant by regularizing with a diagonal matrix formed directly from $J^TJ$ instead of with an arbitrarily chosen identity matrix:</p> \[(J^\top J + \gamma\text{diag}(J^\top J))\delta\beta = J^\top(y - f(x,\beta+\delta\beta)).\] <p>A diagonal matrix (rather than one arbitrarily located nonzero elements) is added for regularization to preserve symmetricity.</p> <h2 id="jax-for-physics--informed-source-separation">JAX for Physics–Informed Source Separation</h2> <p>JAX is an incredible Python library that facilitates the use of automatic differentiation to easily compute Jacobians for numerical optimization (and anywhere else they may be used, such as in the numerical solution of nonlinear systems of ordinary differential equations using Newton’s method). One can also use it for just–in–time (JIT) compilation but we do not do so here. This library forms the backbone of another called JAXopt, where JAXopt has an intuitive interface for calling a routine that uses the Levenberg–Marquardt algorithm to solve a least–squares problem, such as the one we posed using physics–informed regularization. The following illustrates how to solve the optimization problem we’ve discussed so far through JAXopt.</p> <p>First, imports:</p> <p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">python import numpy as np import matplotlib.pyplot as plt import jax import jax.numpy as jnp import jaxopt </code></p> <p>Next, define helper functions for finite–difference simulation of the superposition of advecting signals:</p> <p>```python # helper functions def get_fwd_diff_op(u, dx): n = u.shape[0] main_diag = -1 * np.ones(n) super_diag = np.ones(n - 1) K = np.diag(main_diag) + np.diag(super_diag, k=1) K[-1, 0] = 1 return K * (1 / dx)</p> <p>def get_bwd_diff_op(u, dx): n = u.shape[0] main_diag = np.ones(n) sub_diag = -1 * np.ones(n - 1) K = np.diag(main_diag) + np.diag(sub_diag, k=-1) K[0, 0] = 1 K[0, -1] = -1 return K * (1 / dx)</p> <p>def get_u_next(u_curr, a, dt, Kfwd, Kbwd): D = Kbwd if a &gt;= 0.0 else Kfwd return u_curr - (a * dt) * (D @ u_curr)</p> <p>def get_u0(x, mu): return np.exp(-((x - mu) ** 2) / 0.0002) / np.sqrt(0.0002 * np.pi) ```</p> <p>Then, simulate the individual advection of two Gaussian pulses traveling towards and through each other:</p> <p>```python # space x0, xf = 0.0, 1.0 n = 2**7 x = np.linspace(x0, xf, num=n, endpoint=False) dx = x[1] - x[0]</p> <h1 id="speed">speed</h1> <p>c1 = 10.0 c2 = -c1</p> <h1 id="time">time</h1> <p>t0, tf = 0.0, 0.02 courant_number = 0.99 dt = courant_number * dx / max(abs(c1), abs(c2)) N_steps = int(np.ceil((tf - t0) / dt)) dt = (tf - t0) / N_steps ts = np.linspace(t0, tf, N_steps + 1, endpoint=True)</p> <h1 id="snapshots">snapshots</h1> <p>U1 = np.zeros((n, N_steps + 1)) U2 = np.zeros((n, N_steps + 1))</p> <p>mu1 = 0.4 mu2 = 1.0 - mu1 u1_curr = get_u0(x, mu1) u2_curr = get_u0(x, mu2) U1[:, 0] = u1_curr U2[:, 0] = u2_curr</p> <h1 id="fd-operators">FD operators</h1> <p>Kfwd = get_fwd_diff_op(u1_curr, dx) Kbwd = get_bwd_diff_op(u1_curr, dx)</p> <h1 id="simulate">simulate</h1> <p>for j in range(1, N_steps + 1): u1_curr = get_u_next(u1_curr, c1, dt, Kfwd, Kbwd) U1[:, j] = u1_curr</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>u2_curr = get_u_next(u2_curr, c2, dt, Kfwd, Kbwd)
U2[:, j] = u2_curr

if j % 100 == 0:
    print(f" Step {j:4d}/{N_steps:4d}, t = {ts[j]:.5f}")
</code></pre></div></div> <h1 id="compute-superposition-solution">compute superposition solution</h1> <p>U = U1 + U2 ```</p> <p>Next, visualize the individual PDE solutions and their superposition (which will serve as our observed data that we wish to decompose via physics–informed source separation):</p> <p>```python # plot Minkowski diagrams plt.figure() plt.imshow(U1, extent=(x0, xf, 0, tf), aspect=’auto’) plt.xlabel(‘t’) plt.ylabel(‘x’) plt.title(‘U1’) plt.colorbar() plt.show()</p> <p>plt.figure() plt.imshow(U2, extent=(x0, xf, 0, tf), aspect=’auto’) plt.xlabel(‘t’) plt.ylabel(‘x’) plt.title(‘U2’) plt.colorbar() plt.show()</p> <p>plt.figure() plt.imshow(U, extent=(x0, xf, 0, tf), aspect=’auto’) plt.xlabel(‘t’) plt.ylabel(‘x’) plt.title(‘U1 + U2’) plt.colorbar() plt.show() <br/> ```</p> <p>After that, define helper functions for computing the residual that will be minimized:</p> <p>```python def dUdt_center(U, dt): return (U[2:, 1:-1] - U[:-2, 1:-1]) / (2 * dt)</p> <p>def dUdx_center(U, dx): return (U[1:-1, 2:] - U[1:-1, :-2]) / (2 * dx)</p> <p>def pde_res(U, c, dt, dx): return dUdt_center(U, dt) + c * dUdx_center(U, dx)</p> <p>def get_residual(U_obs, dx, dt, c1, c2, reg_pde1, reg_pde2, mu, lam_1, lam_2, x): nx, nt = U_obs.shape U12 = x.reshape((2 * nx, nt)) U1, U2 = U12[:nx, :], U12[nx:, :]</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>r_dec  = U1 + U2 - U_obs
r_pde1 = 2.0 * jnp.sqrt(reg_pde1) * pde_res(U1, c1, dt, dx)
r_pde2 = 2.0 * jnp.sqrt(reg_pde2) * pde_res(U2, c2, dt, dx)

neg1 = jnp.minimum(U1, 0.0)
neg2 = jnp.minimum(U2, 0.0)

r_pen1 = jnp.sqrt(mu) * neg1
r_pen2 = jnp.sqrt(mu) * neg2

r_mm1 = jnp.sum(lam_1 * (-neg1))
r_mm2 = jnp.sum(lam_2 * (-neg2))

return jnp.concatenate([
    r_dec.ravel(),
    r_pde1.ravel(),
    r_pde2.ravel(),
    r_pen1.ravel(),
    r_pen2.ravel(),
    jnp.atleast_1d(r_mm1),
    jnp.atleast_1d(r_mm2),
])     ```
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Now pose the physics–informed source separation problem with JAX’s <em>jax.numpy</em> syntax. With residuals defined in this way, the Levenberg–Marquardt algorithm can be implemented to compute optimal $U_1$ and $U_2$ through the <em>jaxopt.LevenbergMarquardt</em> method:</p> <p>```python nx, nt = U.shape x = jnp.concatenate([U, U], axis=0).ravel()</p> <p>lam_pde1 = 1e-1 lam_pde2 = 1e-1</p> <p>mu = 10.0 mu_max = 1e5 outer_iters = 10 lm_maxiter = 300</p> <p>lam_1 = jnp.zeros_like(U) lam_2 = jnp.zeros_like(U)</p> <p>prev_viol = jnp.inf for k in range(outer_iters): print(k)</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>x = jaxopt.LevenbergMarquardt(
    residual_fun=lambda x_: get_residual(U, dx, dt, c1, c2, lam_pde1, lam_pde2, mu, lam_1, lam_2, x_),
    maxiter=lm_maxiter
).run(x).params

U12 = x.reshape((2 * nx, nt))
U1, U2 = U12[:nx, :], U12[nx:, :]

neg1 = jnp.minimum(U1, 0.0)
neg2 = jnp.minimum(U2, 0.0)

lam_1 = jnp.maximum(0.0, lam_1 - mu * neg1)
lam_2 = jnp.maximum(0.0, lam_2 - mu * neg2)

viol = jnp.sqrt(jnp.linalg.norm(neg1, ord='fro')**2 + jnp.linalg.norm(neg2, ord='fro')**2)
if float(viol) &lt; 0.8 * float(prev_viol):
    mu = min(mu_max, 2.0 * mu)
prev_viol = viol
</code></pre></div></div> <p>U_hat = np.array(x.reshape((2 * nx, nt))) U1_hat, U2_hat = U_hat[:nx, :], U_hat[nx:, :] ```</p> <p>Last but not least, visualize the sources inferred through our solved physics–informed source separation problem:</p> <p>```python # plot Minkowski diagrams of inferred plt.figure() plt.imshow(U1_hat, extent=(x0, xf, 0, tf), aspect=’auto’) plt.xlabel(‘t’) plt.ylabel(‘x’) plt.title(‘U1_hat’) plt.colorbar() plt.show()</p> <p>plt.figure() plt.imshow(U2_hat, extent=(x0, xf, 0, tf), aspect=’auto’) plt.xlabel(‘t’) plt.ylabel(‘x’) plt.title(‘U2_hat’) plt.colorbar() plt.show() ```</p> <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2> <p>In this post we demonstrated how to use JAX and JAXopt to implement the Levenberg–Marquardt algorithm for solving a least–squares problem whose objective function is formulated using the method of multipliers (aka, augmented Lagrangian method). This was applied to physics–informed source separation of the superposition of two advecting signals, with physics prescribed by 1D linear advection.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="numerical-methods"/><category term="ML"/><category term="optimization"/><category term="PDEs"/><category term="inverse-problems"/><category term="physics-informed"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Formulation and numerical solution of a PDE source separation inverse problem that is regularized with physics--informed a priori information.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Google Gemini updates: Flash 1.5, Gemma 2 and Project Astra</title><link href="https://jburz2001.github.io/blog/2024/google-gemini-updates-flash-15-gemma-2-and-project-astra/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Google Gemini updates: Flash 1.5, Gemma 2 and Project Astra"/><published>2024-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jburz2001.github.io/blog/2024/google-gemini-updates-flash-15-gemma-2-and-project-astra</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jburz2001.github.io/blog/2024/google-gemini-updates-flash-15-gemma-2-and-project-astra/"><![CDATA[<p>May 14, 2024 We’re introducing a series of updates across the Gemini family of models, including the new 1.5 Flash, our lightweight model for speed and efficiency, and Project Astra, our vision for the future of AI assistants. In December, we launched our first natively multimodal model Gemini 1.0 in three sizes: Ultra, Pro and Nano. Just a few months later we released 1.5 Pro, with enhanced performance and a breakthrough long context window of 1 million tokens.Developers and enterprise customers have been putting 1.5 Pro to use in incredible ways and finding its long context window, multimodal reasoning capabilities and impressive overall performance incredibly useful.We know from user feedback that some applications need lower latency and a lower cost to serve. This inspired us to keep innovating, so today, we’re introducing Gemini 1.5 Flash: a model that’s lighter-weight than 1.5 Pro, and designed to be fast and efficient to serve at scale.Both 1.5 Pro and 1.5 Flash are available in public preview with a 1 million token context window in Google AI Studio and Vertex AI. And now, 1.5 Pro is also available with a 2 million token context window via waitlist to developers using the API and to Google Cloud customers.We’re also introducing updates across the Gemini family of models, announcing our next generation of open models, Gemma 2, and sharing progress on the future of AI assistants, with Project Astra.Context lengths of leading foundation models compared with Gemini 1.5’s 2 million token capability1.5 Flash is the newest addition to the Gemini model family and the fastest Gemini model served in the API. It’s optimized for high-volume, high-frequency tasks at scale, is more cost-efficient to serve and features our breakthrough long context window.While it’s a lighter weight model than 1.5 Pro, it’s highly capable of multimodal reasoning across vast amounts of information and delivers impressive quality for its size.The new Gemini 1.5 Flash model is optimized for speed and efficiency, is highly capable of multimodal reasoning and features our breakthrough long context window.1.5 Flash excels at summarization, chat applications, image and video captioning, data extraction from long documents and tables, and more. This is because it’s been trained by 1.5 Pro through a process called “distillation,” where the most essential knowledge and skills from a larger model are transferred to a smaller, more efficient model.Read more about 1.5 Flash in our updated Gemini 1.5 technical report, on the Gemini technology page, and learn about 1.5 Flash’s availability and pricing.Over the last few months, we’ve significantly improved 1.5 Pro, our best model for general performance across a wide range of tasks.Beyond extending its context window to 2 million tokens, we’ve enhanced its code generation, logical reasoning and planning, multi-turn conversation, and audio and image understanding through data and algorithmic advances. We see strong improvements on public and internal benchmarks for each of these tasks.1.5 Pro can now follow increasingly complex and nuanced instructions, including ones that specify product-level behavior involving role, format and style. We’ve improved control over the model’s responses for specific use cases, like crafting the persona and response style of a chat agent or automating workflows through multiple function calls. And we’ve enabled users to steer model behavior by setting system instructions.We added audio understanding in the Gemini API and Google AI Studio, so 1.5 Pro can now reason across image and audio for videos uploaded in Google AI Studio. And we’re now integrating 1.5 Pro into Google products, including Gemini Advanced and in Workspace apps.Read more about 1.5 Pro in our updated Gemini 1.5 technical report and on the Gemini technology page.Gemini Nano is expanding beyond text-only inputs to include images as well. Starting with Pixel, applications using Gemini Nano with Multimodality will be able to understand the world the way people do — not just through text, but also through sight, sound and spoken language.Read more about Gemini 1.0 Nano on Android.Today, we’re also sharing a series of updates to Gemma, our family of open models built from the same research and technology used to create the Gemini models.We’re announcing Gemma 2, our next generation of open models for responsible AI innovation. Gemma 2 has a new architecture designed for breakthrough performance and efficiency, and will be available in new sizes.The Gemma family is also expanding with PaliGemma, our first vision-language model inspired by PaLI-3. And we’ve upgraded our Responsible Generative AI Toolkit with LLM Comparator for evaluating the quality of model responses.Read more on the Developer blog.As part of Google DeepMind’s mission to build AI responsibly to benefit humanity, we’ve always wanted to develop universal AI agents that can be helpful in everyday life. That’s why today, we’re sharing our progress in building the future of AI assistants with Project Astra (advanced seeing and talking responsive agent).To be truly useful, an agent needs to understand and respond to the complex and dynamic world just like people do — and take in and remember what it sees and hears to understand context and take action. It also needs to be proactive, teachable and personal, so users can talk to it naturally and without lag or delay.While we’ve made incredible progress developing AI systems that can understand multimodal information, getting response time down to something conversational is a difficult engineering challenge. Over the past few years, we’ve been working to improve how our models perceive, reason and converse to make the pace and quality of interaction feel more natural.Building on Gemini, we’ve developed prototype agents that can process information faster by continuously encoding video frames, combining the video and speech input into a timeline of events, and caching this information for efficient recall.By leveraging our leading speech models, we also enhanced how they sound, giving the agents a wider range of intonations. These agents can better understand the context they’re being used in, and respond quickly, in conversation.With technology like this, it’s easy to envision a future where people could have an expert AI assistant by their side, through a phone or glasses. And some of these capabilities are coming to Google products, like the Gemini app and web experience, later this year.We’ve made incredible progress so far with our family of Gemini models, and we’re always striving to advance the state-of-the-art even further. By investing in a relentless production line of innovation, we’re able to explore new ideas at the frontier, while also unlocking the possibility of new and exciting Gemini use cases.Learn more about Gemini and its capabilities. Your information will be used in accordance with Google’s privacy policy.</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>      Done. Just one step more.
    
      Check your inbox to confirm your subscription.
    You are already subscribed to our newsletter.
    You can also subscribe with a
    different email address
    
    .
    
  Let’s stay in touch. Get the latest news from Google in your inbox.
          Follow Us
</code></pre></div></div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We’re sharing updates across our Gemini family of models and a glimpse of Project Astra, our vision for the future of AI assistants.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Displaying External Posts on Your al-folio Blog</title><link href="https://jburz2001.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Displaying External Posts on Your al-folio Blog"/><published>2022-04-23T23:20:09+00:00</published><updated>2022-04-23T23:20:09+00:00</updated><id>https://jburz2001.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jburz2001.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog/"><![CDATA[<h3>External Posts on Your al-folio Blog</h3> <p>If you prefer publishing blog posts on medium.com or other external sources, starting version v0.5.0, <a href="https://github.com/alshedivat/al-folio">al-folio</a> lets you to display your external posts in the blog feed of your website! 🎉🎉</p> <p>Configuring external sources of super simple. After upgrading to v0.5.0, just add the following section to your _config.yml:</p> <pre>external_sources:<br />  - name: medium.com  # name of the source (arbitrary string)<br />    rss_url: <a href="https://medium.com/@al-folio/feed">https://medium.com/@&lt;your-medium-username&gt;/feed</a></pre> <p>The example above adds your medium.com blog post feed as an external source. But you can add arbitrary RSS feeds as sources.</p> <p>Any questions or suggestions? 👉 Start <a href="https://github.com/alshedivat/al-folio/discussions">a discussion on GitHub</a>!</p> <p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&amp;referrerSource=full_rss&amp;postId=b60a1d241a0a" width="1" height="1" alt=""/></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry></feed>